<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>InterMine</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>InterMine is an general-purpose object-oriented data warehouse system
  developed as part of the <ulink url="http://www.flymine.org">FlyMine</ulink>
  project and made available as stand-alone open-source software.</para>

  <para>InterMine is capable of efficiently storing and retrieving large
  (multi-gigabyte) quantities of data from user-defined sources, performing
  integration where necessary. The data from each source should conform to a
  model description which can be provided in one of many formats such as UML,
  OWL and XML Schema. However, the system can be easily extended to handle
  data, and models, in any format required. The source of each piece of merged
  data can be tracked so that the system can prioritise information from
  sources that are considered reliable.</para>

  <para>The resultant database can be queried through a Java API or via an
  OQL-like query language. Both approaches can be used transparently by remote
  users as a result of InterMine's support for SOAP and WSDL standards. If a
  graphical query interface is required the system can automatically generate
  a customisable web front end with an integrated help system. All queries are
  mapped to the same internal representation regardless of the interface
  used.</para>

  <para>A stand-alone SQL query optimiser module automatically analyses all
  such queries submitted to the underlying database to try and make use, in
  full or part, of precomputed results in order to improve response times for
  users. In-built caching and paging of results further reduce load on the
  database. This enables InterMine to provide efficient access for a large
  number of users despite the potential size of the database.</para>

  <para>Included in the <ulink url="doc/software/index.xml">full
  documentation</ulink> is an <ulink
  url="doc/software/about/example.xml">example application</ulink> and a more
  <ulink url="doc/software/about/overview.xml">technical overview</ulink>.
  InterMine was originally developed as the software infrastructure for the
  <ulink url="http://www.flymine.org">FlyMine</ulink> project, an integrated
  genomic database, but is suited to many object warehousing
  applications.</para>
</article>