<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial2: <emphasis>Navigating object details pages</emphasis></title>

    <para>This tutorial will guide you through the structure of the
    object details pages and how to navigate them.  The object details
    page for the zen gene will be used as an example.  All object
    details pages have the same basic structure and so this example
    can be extended to other items in the database.</para>

    <para>Enter the gene symbol 'zen' into the quick search box to
    access the object details page for this gene. See tutorial1 for
    more information on the quick search.</para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetails1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    

    <para>The object details page contains the following sections:</para>


    <para>Summary for selected gene: The left-hand side of the object
    details page always provides a summary of the item being
    viewed. This summary includes the main attributes of the item.
    For genes, the main attributes are the identifier, name, symbol
    and organismDbID.  The organismDbID is the main identifier of the
    relevant model organsim database - ie FlyBase for any Drosophila
    melanogaster genes, and so for fly genes, this attribute will
    always be an FBgn identifier.  The 'identifier' attribute contains
    any main secondary identifer used for that particular organism.
    For D. melanogaster genes this is the CGXXXX identifier.  </para>

    <para>Further information for this gene: Below the summary is
    always a section for further information.  This contains links to
    external databases where appropriate - a link is provided to the
    relevant gene report in FlyBase for D. melanogaster genes.  Below
    the external links is an inset of the GBrowse genome viewer.  This
    will be present on the object details page for any genomic
    feature. Click on the GBrowse image to go to the full genome
    browser, from where you can add additional tracks of information
    and naviaagte around the genome.</para>

    <para>Other information: The right hand side of the object details
    page always contains a set of summary tables and links to related
    items. Any data not available for the particular item being viewed
    will be greyed and crossed out. For example, the zen gene has no
    clone or microArrayResult information:</para>



       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetails2.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    

  
    <para>For each related item, there is a summary and a link to the
    details page for that item.  Expand the GoAnnotations and Proteins
    links for the zen gene to see the summary tables for these related
    items:</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetails3.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
     


     <para>From the protein summary table, click on the [details...]
     link.  This will take you to the object details page for the
     ZEN1_DROME protein:</para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetails4.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    

     <para>Notice that the layout of the object details page for the
     ZEN1_DROME protein is the same as that for the zen gene.  Notice
     the 'trail' in the top left hand corner above the summary.  This
     allows you to see where you have navigated from.  Clicking on the
     'gene' link of the trail will take you back to the zen gene
     object details page.</para>

      <para>Look at the links to items related to the ZEN1_PROTEIN.
      Notice that here there are several links to useful protein-based
      information. Notice that there is also a link back to the zen
      gene.  Expand the links for 'Interactions' and 'proteinFeatures'
      to view the summary tables for the related items.  The
      proteinFeatures link contains family and domain information for
      the ZEN1_DROME protein (from Interpro). Click on the
      [details...] link for one of the domains, to navigate to its
      object details page. Use the 'trail' to go back to the
      ZEN1_DROME protein. </para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetails5.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
   


<para> Click on the [details...] link from the Regions link. FlyMine
contains modelled 3-D structural predictions for certain regions of
D. melanogaster proteins.  The regions roughly correspond to Pfam
domains.  The regions link allows you to access the structural
information for any regions which have been modelled.  From the
ProteinRegion object details page, expand the 'object',
'proteinFeature' and 'structure' links to view the domain and location
for which a structure was modelled and information about the actual
modelled structure.  Follow the [details...] link for the
'modelledProteinStructure' for more details about the
structure:</para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetails6.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    



<para>Use the 'trail' to navigate back to the zen gene object details
page.  The above should have given you an idea of how to navigate
around and browse the database via the object details pages for
related items in the database.</para>


<para>Underneath each object details page is a set of related template
queries.  These templates are queries that can be run with the type of
item you are viewing and will be set to run with the identifier of the
item you are viewing. (note: this does not necessarily mean there will
be results available for the particular item you are viewing). See
tutorial2 for more details on running template queries.</para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetails7.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
     


  </section>
</article>
