<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->

<article>


    <sect1>
       <title>Tutorial2: </title>

       <para>This page will guide you through the query: Show the fields for the gene object 'CG10000'.  The aim of this query tutorial is to show you how to constrain the objects belonging to a particular class. It will also show you how to display all the attributes (fields) of that object in the query results (as opposed to selecting particular fields). This query involves:
</para>


        <para>
          <orderedlist>
             <listitem>Selecting the Gene class</listitem>
             <listitem>Constraining the Gene name field to 'CG10000'.</listitem>
             <listitem>Selecting the Gene class to show all the fields of 'CG10000' in the results output</listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>



     <para>
         <orderedlist>
            <listitem>Select the starting point for your query. In this case, Gene.</listitem>
          
	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="classSelection1" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>


            <listitem>The model browser will now be displaying the Gene class and it's fields.  Navigate to the Name field and press -> (constrain).  The name field will be added to the constaints list and a box will appear allowing you to add your constraint.  Write 'CG10000' into the constraints box (note: this is case sensitive) and press Add to query. The constaints list should now show the Gene name constained to = CG10000.</listitem>  


	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="classSelection1.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </entry>

           
            <listitem>You now need to select the Gene class to 'show' in the results output.  In the Model browser click on 'show' next to the Gene class name.  A box showing you have selected the Gene class will appear in the Fields for output list.</listitem>


	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="classSelection1.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </entry>

           
            <listitem>Press 'Show results' to view the CG10000 gene object in the results page.  As you selected the Gene class to 'show' in the output rather than fields of the Gene class, you will now be able to view data associated with all the fields of this Gene object.  Note that some of these fields are browsable.</listitem>

 

	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="classSelection1.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </entry>

     </orderedlist>
     </para>
  </sect1>

</article>
