<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial 5: Exporting Data</title>

    <para>Data can be exported from the result pages in various
    formats - excel (or open office) format, comma separated values,
    tab separated values, or for items with sequences, FASTA format
    (see below).</para> 

    <para>This tutorial will illustrate how to export data from a
    results table and from a bag. As an example, run the template
    'Search for GO annotations for a particular gene' (Gene Ontology
    aspect) for the default value 'CG11348'. Currently, either the
    entire results table or specific columns can be exported. If
    nothing is selected, the entire data set will be exported. If you
    do not wish to export certain columns, then hide these columns
    using the 'hide' option in the column header.</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="export-results.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

   <para>To export a FASTA file of sequences you must create a query
   which returns the object details for each object you want to export
   (e.g. a set of Gene or Protein objects details, as opposed to
   simple attributes such as the gene symbol or identifier).</para>

   <para>Some template queries will return results suitable for
   exporting FASTA files. Find the template 'Output genes from a
   particular organism in a format suitable for creating a FASTA
   database' (Genomics aspect).</para>

   <para>The first column of the results table contains the object
   details of the genes, including a link to the FASTA sequences. To
   export the sequences, hide the columns which do not have any FASTA
   links and click on 'Export in FASTA format' at the bottom of the
   page. Only the sequences will be retrieved and downloaded.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="export-fasta.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>Values stored in bags can also be exported. To export the
    contents of a bag, click on the bag name on the 'history'
    page. This will display the contents of the bag as a results page
    - with the export options available at the bottom of the
    page. Currently, it is not possible to export single items from
    the bag. Therefore, it is not necessary to tick any check-boxes in
    the bag as the whole bag will always be exported.</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="export-bag.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
       </mediaobject>

  </section>
</article>
