<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial 5: Exporting Data</title>

    <para>Data can be exported from the result pages in various
    formats - excel (or open office) format, comma separated values,
    tab separated values, or for items with sequences, FASTA format
    (see below).</para> 

    <para>This tutorial will illustrate how to export data from a
    results table and from a bag. As an example, run the template
    'gene --> GO terms' (Gene Ontology aspect) for the default value
    'CG11348'. Currently, either the entire results table or specific
    columns can be exported. If nothing is selected, the entire data
    set will be exported. If you do not wish to export certain
    columns, then hide these columns using the 'hide' option in the
    column header.</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="export-results.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

   <para>If the results table contains a column with objects that have
   a nucleotide or amino acid sequence, it is possible to export all
   sequences from that column in FASTA format. Currently, the FASTA
   export option will export the sequences belonging to objects in the
   first visible (i.e. not hidden) column only. Therefore, if that
   column does not contain any sequence-linked objects, the FASTA
   export option will not be activated. Columns can be moved to the
   first position by using the arrows in the header. If objects appear
   more than once in the column, the sequence will only be exported
   once.</para>
  

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="export-fasta.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>Values stored in bags can also be exported. To export the
    contents of a bag, click on the bag name on the 'Bags'
    page. This will display the contents of the bag as a results page
    - with the export options available at the bottom of the
    page. Currently, it is not possible to export single items from
    the bag. Therefore, it is not necessary to tick any check-boxes in
    the bag as the whole bag will always be exported.</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="export-bag.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
       </mediaobject>

  </section>
</article>
