<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial 4: Bags and History</title>


    <para>All queries in FlyMine can be performed on lists or 'bags'
    that you create yourself. Bags are holders for lists of data,
    e.g. a list of gene identifiers. Saved bags of data can be used to
    constrain queries (either in a template query or in the
    QueryBuilder), perform logical operations (union, intersect,
    subtract) and can be exported.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Bags can be created from an external source:
      click on 'Bags' on the top menu bar of any FlyMine page and type
      or past in a list of identifiers, or upload a file containing
      the list.</para></listitem>
 
      <listitem><para>Data from previous queries can also be saved
      into a bag. To save your data to a bag select the required data
      on a result page and either add it to an existing bag or save it
      to a new bag, using the boxes displayed underneath the
      results. Selecting the check boxes next to the column headings
      will select the entire column for saving. Alternatively,
      individual items can be saved by selecting check boxes next to
      the items.</para></listitem>

   </itemizedlist>

      <para>This tutorial will illustrate how to create bags and how
      to make use of bags. As an example, we will search for the
      orthologues of <emphasis>D. melanogaster</emphasis> eye
      specification genes in <emphasis>D. pseudoobscura</emphasis>. We
      will then export the gene sequences for all the orthologues at
      once. To find the orthologues of the
      <emphasis>D. melanogaster</emphasis> genes in
      <emphasis>D. pseudoobscura</emphasis>, we will first make a bag
      of the <emphasis>D. melanogaster</emphasis> genes. Click on
      'Bags' in the top menu bar.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="bag-homepage.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

     <para>To make your bag:</para>
 
   <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Either type or cut and paste in a list of
      identifiers, or upload a list from a file. As an example, type
      in the gene symbols 'ey', 'eya', 'toy', 'dac' and 'so' into the
      box.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Enter a name for your bag, e.g. 'eye-genes_dmel'
      (or leave the default) by 'Name for new bag'.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Click on 'Make identifier bag' to save your
      bag.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="bag-create.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>Now we want to find all the orthologous genes in
    <emphasis>D. pseudoobscura</emphasis> using an existing
    template. Find the template 'Gene --> Orthologues in one specific
    organism' (Comparative Genomics aspect).</para>

   <para>Any variable in a template query can be constrained to a bag
    (or 'not in' a bag) rather than a single value. Click on the
    check-box below the Synonym value box to constrain the gene
    synonym value to be in a bag. If you have bags saved in your
    'MyMine' the option to constrain each variable to a bag will appear
    automatically. The name of the bag you just created will appear in
    the drop-down menu. Select the right organisms from the two other
    drop-down menus and run the query.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="bag-template.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

   <para>The results table shows the
   <emphasis>D. melanogaster</emphasis> genes with their corresponding
   orthologues in <emphasis>D. pseudoobscura</emphasis>. Only 4 out of
   the 5 <emphasis>D. melanogaster</emphasis> genes have orthologues
   in <emphasis>D. pseudoobscura</emphasis>.</para>

    

   <para>Save the orthologous genes in a new bag:</para>
 
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Click on the check-box in the title of column 4
      which contains the gene symbols for the orthologues. This
      selects all items in the column (on every result page, if more
      than one page). Alternatively, select individual items in the
      column.</para></listitem>

     <listitem><para>At the bottom of the page is an option to save
      the selected results in a new bag. Choose a new bag name
      e.g. 'eye-genes_dpse' and click 'Save'.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="bag-template-results.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>Bags of data, as well as previously executed queries, can be
    retrieved from your MyMine page at the top menu bar on any
    FlyMine page (bags can also be directly accessed through the
    'Bags' link). Your bags and query history will remain available to
    you only for the duration of a session unless you create and use a
    login. If you log in (via button on top menu bar), your bags and
    query history can be stored permanently. Click on 'MyMine' in the
    top menu bar.</para>

   <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="bag-MyMine.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject> 
 
  <para>Find your bags back in 'Bags'.</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="bag-history.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

 
   <para>To find out how to export the contents of a bag, see <ulink
   url="tutorial5-Export.xml">Tutorial 5</ulink>.</para>

 </section>
</article>
