<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial 6: The FlyMine QueryBuilder</title>

    <para>Advanced users can use a flexible query interface</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>to construct their own data mining queries
      across the multiple integrated data sources,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>to modify existing template queries or</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>to create your own template queries.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The QueryBuilder interface enables you to browse through
    classes and fields of the data model, selecting those that you
    wish to constrain and those that you wish to include in your
    results (see user manual for definitions of some terms).</para>

    <para>This tutorial introduces the use of the QueryBuilder to
    alter an existing template. It will start with the template 'For
    the following gene symbol, show its gene identifier' (Gene symbol
    --> Gene identifier) and alter it to collect all gene identifiers
    from genes on the 4th chromosome of
    <emphasis>D. melanogaster</emphasis>. Find the template 'Gene
    symbol --> Gene identifier' (Genomics aspect). Click on 'Edit
    Query'.  This will display the underlying query in the query
    builder. </para>

   <para>The main FlyMine QueryBuilder page is composed of 3 sections:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>The model browser (left) allows you to browse
      through the FlyMine data model, selecting the classes that
      contain the objects you require. Depending on the starting class
      you will be able to navigate to other classes as defined by the
      references between the classes. In other words, to combine
      classes containing the objects you require, you find a path
      through the classes that link together the information you
      require. Within the model browser, classes that can be accessed
      from a parent class (i.e. are linked to the parent class through
      a reference) are shown as fields within that class.  For each
      field within the model browser there is a 'SHOW' and a
      'CONSTRAIN' option. These are used to either select a
      field to show in the results output or to constrain in the
      constraints list.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>The constraints list (right) allows you specify
      the constraints you wish to apply to particular classes and
      fields. A constraint is like a filter - you filter out a subset
      of the objects in a class which have certain characteristics
      (defined by the constraint). To apply a constraint to a field,
      navigate to the field in the model browser and click on the
      'constrain' button next to it. This will add the field to the
      constraints list and bring up a box in which you specify your
      constraint.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Initially, the output fields list (bottom) will
      say 'No fields selected for output'. The output fields list
      shows all fields that you have selected to show in your
      results. To select a field to show in the results output you
      press 'SHOW' next to the field. The order of fields in the
      output fields list can be changed using the arrows or by
      dragging them. Fields can be deleted from the output fields list
      using the x. Fields that have been selected for output will
      appear in a blue box in the model browser and constraint
      list.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="QB-template1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>



     <para>In the next steps, we will change the current
     query to retrieve all genes on the 4th chromosome.</para>

       <itemizedlist>
         <listitem><para>Click on 'Current query' in the top menu bar
         to return to the QueryBuilder.</para></listitem>

         <listitem><para>The right hand side summarises constraints in
         the current query. Note the constraint on Gene symbol to be
         'zen'. Clicking on the red cross next to 'symbol' will delete
         this constraint.</para></listitem>

         <listitem><para>To constrain the current query for genes on
         the 4th chromosome, click on the + sign next to 'chromosome'
         in the column on the left. Click on 'CONSTRAIN' next to
         'identifier' (under 'chromosome'). This brings up a
         'Constrain' section to the right (you might have to scroll
         down to view it). You can enter or select a value for the
         chromosome identifier from the drop-down menu: the identifier
         for the 4th chromosome is '4'. Click 'Add to query' next to
         the drop-down menu.</para></listitem>
       </itemizedlist>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="QB_template2.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

       <itemizedlist>
         <listitem><para>Now we need to constrain the query to return
         only genes from <emphasis>D. melanogaster</emphasis>. Click
         on the + sign next to 'organism' in the column on the
         left. Next, click on 'CONSTRAIN' next to 'name' (under
         'organism'). This brings up a 'Constrain' section to the
         right. Select 'Drosophila melanogaster' and click on 'Add to
         query' next to the drop-down menu.</para></listitem>

         <listitem><para>Finally, we will change the current query so
         that it also returns the FBgn number. To make the FBgn number
         appear on the result page, click on 'SHOW' next to
         'organismDbId' under 'Gene'. 'organismDbId' will now appear
         in blue and can be find in the output section below. The
         order of the columns can be changed by clicking and dragging
         the output boxes. Scroll down and click 'Show results' to run
         the query again.</para></listitem>
       </itemizedlist>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="QB-template3.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>To build a new query from scratch, access the FlyMine
    QueryBuilder at the bottom of the FlyMine home page or by choosing
    a query starting point at the bottom of an aspect page.</para>

  </section>
</article>


