<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial 2: Navigating object details pages</title>

    <para>For every object in the FlyMine database there is an object
    details page which provides all the fields, references and
    collections for that object along with additional information such
    as the GBrowse genome viewer for sequence features (see the User
    Manual for an explanation of these concepts). All object details
    pages have the same basic structure. Object details pages can be
    accessed using the Quick Search on the FlyMine homepage, or from
    result tables by clicking on the links, where available.</para>

    <para>This tutorial will guide you through the structure of the
    object details pages and how to navigate them. The object details
    page for the <emphasis>zen</emphasis> gene will be used as an
    example. Enter the gene symbol <emphasis>zen</emphasis> into the
    Quick Search box on the FlyMine home page (See <ulink
    url="tutorial1-QuickSearch.xml">Tutorial 1</ulink> for more
    information). The query returns just one result so you are taken
    directly to the object details page for the
    <emphasis>zen</emphasis> gene.</para>

    <para>The top left shows summary information for this gene -
    identifier, name and chromosome coordinates. Use the '+' boxes
    next to 'proteins', 'synonyms', etc.  to open inline tables with
    more details. The 'FASTA' buttons retrieve sequences for any
    feature they appear next to.</para>

    <para>The top right presents:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>A link to the gene report of the relevant model organism database.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>A GBrowse image for the area surrounding this gene. Clicking
      on the image takes you to the GBrowse genome viewer.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="odp-gene-top.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>Scroll down the page to see 'Other details by aspect'. This
    section has more detailed information about this gene divided into
    'aspects'. The aspects correspond to categories of data shown on
    the FlyMine home page. Look at the Genomics aspect:</para>

   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para>Entries in green show fields directly related to
    this gene. Use '+' boxes to open summary tables. For example,
    opening 'UTRs' will summarise 5' and 3' UTR
    information.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Entries in black text allow you to see the results
    of predefined queries run for this gene ('templates' See <ulink
    url="tutorial3-Templates.xml">Tutorial 3</ulink>).  Those
    shown in light grey did not return any results.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>'[details...]' links take you to object details
    pages for related database entries.</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="odp-gene-bottom.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

     <para>Scroll back up to the top of the page and click the
    '[details...]'  link next to 'proteins'. This page presents more
    information about the 'ZEN_DROME' protein.  The trail at the top
    keeps track of [details...] links you have followed.</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="odp-protein-top.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>


  </section>
</article>
