<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->

<article>


    <sect1>
       <title>Tutorial3: Show all the orthologues between <span class="organism">Drosophila melanogaster</span> and <span class="organism">Anopheles gambiae</span> and the method used to determine them.</title>


       <para>This page will guide you through the query: Show all the
       orthologues between <span class="organism">Drosophila
       melanogaster</span> and <span class="organism">Anopheles
       gambiae</span> and the method used to determine them.  The aim
       of this query tutorial is to show you how a relation between
       BioEntity objects (eg genes) is linked via a subject and an
       object and how to get information from the Evidence
       class.  This query involves:
       </para>

   
        <para>
          <orderedlist>
             <listitem>Selecting the Orthologue class.</listitem>
             <listitem>Constraining the objects of the relations to
             <span class="organism">Drosophila melanogaster</span> and
             constraining the subjects of the relations to <span
             class="organism">Anopheles gambiae</span>.</listitem>
             <listitem>Constraining and adding fields from the
             Evidence class to show how the orthologues were
             determined.</listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>


    <para>
         <orderedlist>
            <listitem>Select the starting point for your query. In this case, Orthologue.</listitem>
          
	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="classSelection2" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>


          <listitem>The model browser will now be displaying the
          Orthologue class and it's fields.  The orthologue class is a
          subclass (specialisation) of the Relation class. The
          Relation class links two BioEntity objects that have some
          type of relationship with each other. Every relation has a
          subject and an object. If two genes are orthologues, one of
          the genes will be the subject of the relation and the other
          the object. You need to add constraints to specify that you
          want the objects of the orthologue relations to be BioEntity
          objects (in this case genes) from <span
          class="organism">Drosophila melanogaster</span> and the
          subjects of the relation to be BioEntity objects from <span
          class="organism">Anopheles gambiae</span>.  The Relation
          class has three fields: evidence, object and subject.
          Expand the object field.  The object field has a link
          (reference) to the Organism class.  Expand the organism
          class.  Click on the constrain arrow next to the name field
          of the Organism class and add the constraint: LIKE
          %melanogaster.  Click on 'Add to results' to add this to the
          constraints list.  In the same way, constrain the Organism
          name field of the subject to: LIKE %gambiae.</listitem>




	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="constrainRelation1" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>


          

          <listitem>You want to display the name of the object and the subject
          in your results.  In this case the object and the subject are genes,
          so the name fields will refer to the gene name.  Select the name
          fields of the object and the subject to show in the
          results.</listitem> 



	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="showFields2" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>




         <listitem>You now need to add fields to show how the orthologues were
         determined.  The Evidence class links relation data to an
         AnalysisResult class.  Click on the constrain arrow next to the
         evidence field of the Relation class.  Constrain this to type:
         AnalysisResult, and press 'Add to query' to add the constraint to the
         constraints list.</listitem> 

	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="constrainEvidence2" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>




	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="constrainEvidence1" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>



        <listitem>As you constrained the Evidence class to type =
        AnalysisResult above, the AnalysisResult class will now be displayed
        in the model browser.  You want to show the analysis in your results.
        Click on show next to the analysis field to add this to the 'Fields
        selected for output'</listitem> 



	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="showFields3" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>




         <listitem>Press 'Show results' to view your results in the results page:</listitem>


	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="resultsQuery4" format="PNG"/>
	  </entry>



  </orderedlist>
  </para>
</sect1>
</article>
