<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->

<article>


    <sect1>
       <title>Tutorial3: <span class="tutorial">Show all the orthologues between <span class="organism">Drosophila melanogaster</span> and <span class="organism">Anopheles gambiae</span></span></title>


       <para>This page will guide you through the query: Show all the
       orthologues between <span class="organism">Drosophila
       melanogaster</span> and <span class="organism">Anopheles
       gambiae</span>. The aim of this query tutorial is to show you
       how a relation between BioEntity objects (eg genes) is linked
       via a subject and an object. This query involves:
       </para>

   
        <para>
          <orderedlist>
             <listitem>Selecting the Orthologue class.</listitem>
             <listitem>Constraining the objects of the relations to
             <span class="organism">Drosophila melanogaster</span> and
             constraining the subjects of the relations to <span
             class="organism">Anopheles gambiae</span>.</listitem>
             
          </orderedlist>
        </para>


    <para>
         <orderedlist>
            <listitem>Select the starting point for your query. In this case, Orthologue.</listitem>
          
	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="classSelection2"/>
	  </entry>


          <listitem>The model browser will now be displaying the
          Orthologue class and it's fields.  The orthologue class is a
          subclass (specialisation) of the Relation class. The
          Relation class links two BioEntity objects that have some
          type of relationship with each other. Every relation has a
          subject and an object. If two genes are orthologues, one of
          the genes will be the subject of the relation and the other
          the object. You need to add constraints to specify that you
          want the objects of the orthologue relations to be BioEntity
          objects (in this case genes) from <span
          class="organism">Drosophila melanogaster</span> and the
          subjects of the relation to be BioEntity objects from <span
          class="organism">Anopheles gambiae</span>.  The Relation
          class has three fields: evidence, object and subject.
          Expand the object field.  The object field has a link
          (reference) to the Organism class.  Expand the organism
          class.  Click on the constrain arrow next to the name field
          of the Organism class and add the constraint: LIKE
          %melanogaster.  Click on 'Add to results' to add this to the
          constraints list.  In the same way, constrain the Organism
          name field of the subject to: LIKE %gambiae.</listitem>




	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="constrainRelation1"/>
	  </entry>


          

          <listitem>You want to display the identifier of the object
          and the subject in your results.  In this case the object
          and the subject are genes, so the identifier fields will
          refer to the gene's main identifier. Select the identifier
          fields of the object and the subject to show in the
          results.</listitem>



	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="showFields2"/>
	  </entry>


         <listitem>Press 'Show results' to view your results in the results page:</listitem>


	  <entry>
	      <inlinegraphic fileref="resultsQuery4temp"/>
	  </entry>



  </orderedlist>
  </para>
</sect1>
</article>
