<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>The query Builder Page</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The FlyMine query builder page is composed of 3 sections: a
        model browser (left), a constraints list (right) and an output fields
        list (bottom). The output fields list will initially say 'No fields
        selected for output'.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Building a FlyMine query involves the following steps (described
        in more detail below):</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select classes and/or fields to constrain.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select classes and /or fields you wish to include in the
        results.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show Results.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The model browser</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The model browser initially displays the class you selected and
        its fields. Some of the fields are references (links) from this class
        to other classes. Class references can be identified by the + box to
        the left, allowing you to expand the class. Expanding a referenced
        class will show you its fields.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Using the model browser you can navigate a path through the
        FlyMine classes to combine the information you require in different
        ways, depending on your starting point.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>There are two options for each class and field in the model
        browser: show and -&gt; (constrain). Use these to select fields from
        the model browser to constrain (in the constraint list) and/or 'show'
        (in the output fields list)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The constraints list</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Constraints are applied to a particular class or field in the
        right hand constraint pane. To add a class or a field to this pane so
        that it can be constrained click on the -&gt; next to the class or
        field. A box allowing you to specify your constraint will appear at
        the bottom of this pane. Add your constraint here and press 'Add to
        query' to add the constraint to the constraint display.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Constraints you have applied are listed in the right hand
        constraints pane. If you are constraining items from more than one
        class, the constraints from a referenced class will be indented
        relative to the parent class. When you select a referenced class to
        constrain, the view in the model browser will change to display the
        fields of that class. The path you have taken through the classes is
        shown at the top of the model browser. You can change the class
        displayed in the browser by clicking on a class name here or on the
        class name in the constraint pane.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you are constraining a referenced class you will be given the
        option to constrain the class to any of the subtypes of that class.
        E.g. The transcript class can be constrained to a number of subtypes
        of transcript (e.g. primary transcript, processed transcript, tRNA
        etc.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To remove a constraint click on the red x next to the
        constraint. To add another constraint to a field already constrained
        (or to change the current constraint) click on 'constrain' next to
        that field. The constraint options will appear at the bottom of the
        pane as before.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The output fields list</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The output fields list is found at the bottom of the page, below
        the model browser. Initially this list will be empty and will say 'No
        fields selected for output'. To display a particular field in the
        results, it must be added to the output fields list by clicking on
        'show', next to the field, in the model browser. To display all the
        fields of a particular class in the results, click on the 'show' next
        to the class name.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Show results</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Press the 'Show Results' button to view the results of your
        query.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All queries run are saved in the query history. If you do not
        give your query a particular name (in the 'Save query' box at the
        bottom of the query builder page), it will be saved as query_n (where
        the number n increments for each query run). To access your query
        history, click on History in the menu bar. Here you can select a query
        to run again or modify in the query builder page. You can also delete
        any queries you no longer wish to keep.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>