<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Introducing InterMine: an example application</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>InterMine provides flexible facilities to integrate, store and
  retrieve data in varying formats from muliple user-specified sources. For a
  demonstration of its capabilities, whilst neglecting most implementation
  details, consider the following example which concerns data describing the
  (simplified) structure of an enterprise. In this case no data integration is
  performed, as only one data source is used.</para>

  <para>Assume that our organisation model is described using the following
  UML diagram, drawn using a graphical editor such as ArgoUML. InterMine is
  able to read such diagrams directly, and so this is often the best way to
  describe data for which no model has been predefined.</para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="example.png" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>It is important to note that InterMine generates Java source code for
  the classes in the model, and transforms all data into instances of these
  classes prior to storage. The canonical form for data is Java objects, but
  InterMine does not favour any particular data file format. For the sake of
  simplicity consider the data to be in the following XML format, which should
  be fairly self-explanatory when read in conjunction with the diagram
  above.</para>

  <programlisting>

&lt;items&gt;
  &lt;item id="1" class="http://www.intermine.org/model/testmodel#Department"&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="name" value="DepartmentA1"/&gt;
    &lt;reference name="manager" ref_id="2"/&gt;
    &lt;collection name="employees"&gt;
      &lt;reference ref_id="2"/&gt;
      &lt;reference ref_id="3"/&gt;
    &lt;/collection&gt;
  &lt;/item&gt;
  &lt;item id="2" class="http://www.intermine.org/model/testmodel#Manager"&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="name" value="EmployeeA1"/&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="fullTime" value="true"/&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="age" value="10"/&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="title" value="Head of marketing"/&gt;
    &lt;reference name="address" ref_id="4"/&gt;
    &lt;reference name="department" ref_id="1"/&gt;
  &lt;/item&gt;
  &lt;item id="3" class="http://www.intermine.org/model/testmodel#Employee"&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="name" value="EmployeeA2"/&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="fullTime" value="true"/&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="age" value="20"/&gt;
    &lt;reference name="address" ref_id="4"/&gt;
    &lt;reference name="department" ref_id="1"/&gt;
  &lt;/item&gt;
  &lt;item id="4" class="http://www.intermine.org/model/testmodel#Address"&gt;
    &lt;attribute name="address" value="Employee Street, AVille"/&gt;
  &lt;/item&gt;
&lt;/items&gt;

    </programlisting>

  <para>Given this data, the model, and some extra configuration information,
  InterMine is capable of storing the data in a relational database. The data
  is subsequently accessible using an object-oriented query language that
  returns Java objects representing the data. The system is capable of
  exposing the datastore to web users using a HTML interface, and other remote
  users using a SOAP interface. Ultimately this means that whilst the
  prerequisites for building an InterMine database include the installation of
  a relational database (eg. PostgreSQL) and a Java runtime environment, end
  users can simply use a web browser or a simple Java API (which accepts
  queries in either an <ulink
  url="../java_query/spec.xml">object-oriented</ulink> or <ulink
  url="../iql_query/spec.xml">OQL-like format</ulink>) to access the
  data.</para>

  <para>A <ulink url="/begin.do">demo</ulink> of the web interface, built
  using a superset of the data above, is publicly accessible. Help is
  available by clicking on the relevant links.</para>

  <para>Also available is a Java client for a demo of the SOAP interface. If
  you have a Java runtime environment installed, simply add the .jar file to
  your CLASSPATH and run java org.intermine.objectstore.query.iql.IqlShell,
  which will display a shell to OQL-like queries remotely against the
  InterMine demo database. For some suitable queries to run consult <ulink
  url="../howto_query.xml">"How to query InterMine"</ulink>. It is also
  possible to use this .jar file to build and run queries from Java using the
  full API.</para>
</article>