<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article>
  <artheader>
    <date>2003-06-30</date>
    <title>Basic tutorial</title>
  </artheader>
  <sect1>
    <para>The tutorial consists of a simple model, some test data for this model and a Java program to query the data. It includes the InterMine jar, its dependencies, the necessary configuration files and a build script. A prerequisite for the tutorial is a Java compiler and interpreter.</para>
    <para>Running the tutorial involves a few simple steps:</para>
    <para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><ulink url="http://download.flymine.org/nightly/">Download</ulink> and unpack the latest InterMine tutorial (intermine-tutorial-xxxxxx)</listitem>
        <listitem>Install the <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</ulink> build tool. Note that the <command>ant</command> executable must be on your PATH</listitem>
        <listitem>Install the <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</ulink> database and create a database named "tutorial". Note that the postmaster must be set up to accept TCP/IP connections ("tcpip_socket=true" in <command>postgresql.conf</command>) from "localhost" (host 127.0.0.1 in <command>pg_ident.conf</command>). Consult the PostgreSQL documentation for more details on configuring access control and database creation</listitem>
        <listitem>Change to the tutorial root directory</listitem>
        <listitem>Modify the "intermine.properties" configuration file to reflect your database username, and password if necessary</listitem>
            <listitem>Run the <command>ant</command> command to view the available build targets. <command>ant run</command> will compile the InterMine system, build a simple model, store some data corresponding to the model (accessing the database), and run some queries to retrieve the data. The tutorial source (<command>src/java/org/intermine/tutorial/SimpleQuery.java</command>) demonstrates how to build a simple query for a model (<command>model/tutorial_model.xml</command>) and navigate the results, which can be compared to the test data (<command>resources/tutorial_data.xml</command>)</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>
