<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article>

	<artheader>
		<date>2003-10-15</date>
		<title>Flymine - How the objectstore's behaviour is affected by the model</title>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Andrew</firstname>
				<surname>Varley</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Matthew</firstname>
				<surname>Wakeling</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
	</artheader>

	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>This document describes how the objectstore is affected by the model.
			It describes the different types of Object Class and Interface, and how they differ.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Characteristics of a model</title>
		<para>The FlyMine database system treats Classes and Interfaces as similarly to Java as possible.
			All objects that are stored in the database must implement/extend the org.flymine.model.InterMineObject interface.
			There is no other restriction that prevents an object being stored in the database.
			All Java Classes and Interfaces generated from a model description implement this interface automatically.</para>
		<para>The model represents the possibilities for searching in the database.
			Fields in the model can take part in the WHERE clause of a query.
			Interfaces and Classes in the model can take part in the the FROM clause of a query.</para>
		<para>Like Java, an Interface may extend multiple Interfaces, but no Classes.
			Also, like Java, a Class may extend a single Class, or not (in which case it implicitly implements java.lang.Object).
			A Class may implement multiple Interfaces, or not.
			If a Class or Interface implements or extends another Class or Interface, it automatically implements and extends everything that Class or Interface implements or extends.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Types of Classes and Interfaces</title>
		<para>This section describes the various types of Class and Interface, and how they can be used in the database.
			All of these types are Classes and Interfaces that extend or implement org.flymine.model.InterMineObject, since other Classes and Interfaces cannot be handled by the FlyMine system.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Interfaces in the model</title>
			<para>These are Interfaces that are well-described in the model.
				They may have fields (unlike Java) - the fields are simulated as getter and setter methods in the Interface.
				One can create an object that is effectively an instance of an interface by using org.flymine.util.DynamicUtil, and these objects can be stored in the database.
				One can create a query with one of these in the FROM clause, to receive a set of objects that can all be cast to the Interface.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Classes in the model</title>
			<para>These are Classes that are well-described in the model.
				They may have fields, but (unlike Java) they do not need to list all the fields in their implemented Interfaces - that is done automatically.
				One can create a new instance of a Class, by using the "new" operator in Java, which is the simplest available method of creating an object.
				One can create a query with one of these in the FROM clause, to receive a set of objects that can all be cast to the Class.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Interfaces not defined by the model</title>
			<para>These are Interfaces that are not mentioned in the model.
				The code for the Interfaces must be written separately - the Flymine Java Code Generation will not oblige.
				The Interface must implement org.flymine.model.InterMineObject - then one can create an object that is effectively an instance of the Interface using org.flymine.util.DynamicUtil, and such objects can be stored in the database.
				These Interfaces cannot however be mentioned in a query, nor can any fields defined by the Interface.
				The only way to retrieve the objects from the database is to generate a query with a super-Interface that is present in the model (for example org.flymine.model.InterMineObject).</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Classes not defined by the model</title>
			<para>These are Classes that are not mentioned in the model.
				The code for the Class must be written separately - the Flymine Java Code Generation will not oblige.
				One can create an instance of the Class by using the "new" operator in Java, and one can store that object in the database.
				These Classes can never be mentioned in a query, nor can any fields defined by the Class.
				The only way to retrieve the objects from the database is to generate a query for a superclass or super-Interface that is present in the model.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Dynamic classes</title>
			<para>These are classes that are created on the spot, for example from an Interface.
				A dynamic class can be generated from a set of classes and interfaces, only one of which can be a class.
				At least one of those classes must implement org.flymine.model.InterMineObject, so that the dynamic class implements it.
				Objects can be created from these classes, and stored in the database.
				A query can only be created with one of these classes in the FROM clause if the class is free of classes and interfaces outside the model</para>
		</sect2>
		<para>The FlyMine database does not treat Classes and Interfaces any differently, except for the following:
			All elements in the FROM clause of a Query must resolve down to a Class.
			Obviously this Class can be dynamically constructed from multiple Interfaces, but not from multiple Classes.
			Likewise, an attempt to form a Class from two interfaces that have a common field name with different types will not work.</para>
	</sect1>
</article>
