<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article id="manualRelationclass">
  <section>
    <title>Relation</title>

    <para>Any two <ulink url="manualBioEntityclass.xml">BioEntity
    objects</ulink> that have some form of relationship to each other are
    linked by the Relation class.</para>

    <para>Relations include orthologue and paralogue relations between two
    BioEntity objects, location relationships (eg an exon has a location on a
    gene. A gene has a location on a chromosome etc) and protein-protein
    interactions.</para>

    <para>Every relation object has a subject and an object. For example, if
    two genes are orthologues, one of the genes will be the subject of the
    relation and the other the object. Because relations are symmetrical (ie
    gene A is an orthologue of Gene B and Gene B is an orthologue of gene A),
    a particular relationship is mapped both ways in the database (ie Gene A
    and Gene B will be linked by 2 relations, one in which Gene A is the
    subject and Gene B the object and one in which Gene A is the object and
    Gene B the subject). If you ask for the subject orthologue of Gene A you
    will get Gene B (and Gene A in this case is the object). However you could
    also ask for the subject orthologue of Gene B and get gene A (in this case
    gene B is the object). i.e for any particular relation object a particular
    BioEntity will be the subject and the other the object. However, there can
    be 2 relation objects relating the same two BioEntity.</para>

    <para>Every BioEntity has a collection of all the object relations it has
    and a collection of all the subject relations it has. The object relations
    collection contains all the relation objects in which the BioEntity is the
    subject. The subject relations collection contains all the relation
    objects in which the BioEntity is object. For example gene A has a
    collection of subjects relations and a collection of object relations.
    Each relation links one BioEntity with another BioEntity.</para>

    <para>To see an example query in which two BioEntity are linked via the
    Relation class see xxxxxxx</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="relationClass1.gif" />
      </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Relation Class</phrase></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</article>
