<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Choosing a starting point</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To build a query using the FlyMine Query Builder you
        must first decide on a starting class for your query.  The
        main classes are displayed on the initial query page and are
        divided into biologically meaniful categories.  This page
        contains a list of classes for which objects exist in the
        database (i.e. classes for which there is data associated).
        Selecting a class will take you to the <ulink
        url="manualQuerybuilder.xml">FlyMine query builder
        page.</ulink></para>

         <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
             <imagedata fileref="classSelection1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

      </listitem>


      <listitem>
        <para>In addition to the above classes a full list of classes
        from which you can start your query can be accessed by
        clicking on the 'List all classes' link (see above
        screenshot).  This takes you to the class chooser page (see
        screenshot below).  This page contains a list of classes for
        which objects exist in the database (i.e. classes for which
        there is data associated). Select the class from which you
        wish to start your query and press the Select button. This
        will take you to the <ulink
        url="manualQuerybuilder.xml">FlyMine query builder
        page.</ulink></para>

         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="classSelectionAll1.png" />
           </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>

       </listitem>


    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Browse the FlyMine model</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The 'Browse model' button (see first screenshot above) allows you to browse the complete FlyMine
        object model. This shows all the classes in FlyMine, some of which do
        not yet have data associated with them</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The number on the right shows the number of objects associated
        with that class</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click on a class name to begin your query with that class</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <mediaobject>
           <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="browsingModel1.png" />
           </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>




  </section>
</article>
