<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Identifiers, Accessions and Synonyms in FlyMine</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>This page describes the meanings and origins of identifiers of
        biological objects in FlyMine. As FlyMine aggregates data from
        multiple sources there are often many different identifiers for the
        same entity. Available identifiers vary between biological object
        type, organism and data source. FlyMine attempts to choose a standard
        or commonly used unique identifier for each biological type and
        retains all other identifiers as synonyms with a reference to their
        source.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BioEntity is the root class of all biological objects in the
        FlyMine model. This has an identifier field that all subclasses (e.g.
        Chromosome, Gene, Exon) inherit. The identifier field is almost always
        populated with a value unique in the context of a particular organism.
        The only time when 'identifier' can be empty is when another primay
        identifier field exists (e.g. Gene, Protein) and a data source has
        only provided the alternative.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In some cases this is a standard identifier (e.g. Protein -
        UNIPROT id), for biological types that are not so widely referenced
        this will be the identifier for the primary data source used (e.g.
        Exon - Ensembl stable id). For some types the identifier is more akin
        to a name than a universal identifier (e.g. Chromsome - 'X'). All
        widely used identifiers that FlyMine has loaded are also stored as
        Synonyms of the BioEntity linked to the source.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Gene - for some organisms there are two commonly used
        identification schemes, for example Drosophila has FlyBase FBgn*** and
        Celera CG***. Gene has an additional identifier field, 'organismDbId',
        which contains the id used in the main annotation database for each
        organism. So for Drosophila 'organismDbId' is a FlyBase id and
        'identifier' is CG*** id. When there is only one main identifier for
        an organism the same id is used in both fields. In addition Gene has
        'name' and 'description' fields. All gene names are stored as
        Synonyms, only one should have the 'isPrimary' flag set to
        true.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Protein - current situation (July 2004) The 'identifier' and
        'primaryAccession' fields of Protein are set to the accession with
        which it was labelled in the source it came from. In many cases this
        will be the UNIPROT primary accession but no verification is performed
        against UNIPROT.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Protein - future plan (~September 2004) - proteins will be
        classified where possible according to UNIPROT. The 'identifier' field
        will be the UNIPROT identifer when available (e.g. 18C_DROME). Protein
        has an additional 'primaryAccession' field which will be the UNIPROT
        primary accession where available (e.g. P16909). All accession numbers
        available in UNIPROT are stored as synonyms with type 'accession'
        (i.e. P16909, Q9VPA8). Only the primary accession will have the
        'isPrimary' flag set to true.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It is conceivable that a data source could provide a Protein
        with a TREMBL identifier/accession which has been superceeded as the
        primary UNIPROT identifier/accesssion by the inclusion of that protein
        in SWISSPROT. This could result in two Protein objects existing in the
        FlyMine database representing the same actual protein - one with the
        current UNIPROT ids, on with TREMBl ids. We aim to run a
        post-processing step to find and correct these situations once we have
        integrated UNIPROT data. The two Proteins would then be merged.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Synonyms represent alternative names and accessions for a
        BioEntity. The 'source' reference points at an InfoSource object (i.e.
        Database, Publication) from which the synonym was loaded. Synonym has
        a 'type' field which defines it as an 'accession' or a 'name'. An
        'isPrimary' flag is set to true if the synonym is the main name or
        accession for that source - e.g. UNIPROT primary accession or main
        FlyBase gene name.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>