<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article id="manualQuickstartBU">
  <section>
    <title>Quick start guide</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>

       <para>The FlyMine query page provides three routes to the data
       in the FlyMine database. These are described in more detail below:</para> 
       
       <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>The FlyMine Query Builder</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Browsing</para>
         </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>Template queries</para>
         </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
     
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="mainPage1.png" />
            </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Main Page</phrase></textobject>
          </mediaobject>

   </section>

   <section>
     <title>1. The FlyMine Query Builder: building complex queries</title>
   
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>FlyMine allows you to construct complex queries across
        multiple integrated data sources using a web interface</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Building a query using the FlyMine query builder involves
        the following steps, which are described in more detail below.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To start a new FlyMine query, choose the starting
            point for your query either from the classes displayed
            (which have been divided into biologically meaniful
            categories) or by selecting the 'List all classes'
            link.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Selecting the class with which to start your query
            will take you to the main query builder page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the model browser, browse to the classes and fields you
            are interested in.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select the classes and/or fields you wish to constrain using
            the -&gt; constrain arrows. Specify your constraints in the right
            hand constraints list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select the classes and/or fields you wish to show in the
            results output using the "show" buttons. The classes/fields
            selected will appear in the output fields list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press 'show results' to view your results in the results
            page.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For a walk-through a simple query see the <ulink
        url="../tutorials/index.xml">tutorials.</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
 
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The FlyMine query builder consists of 3 main sections:</para> 
      

       <orderedlist> 

       <listitem>     
         <para>A. The class chooser</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
         <para>B. The main query builder page</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
         <para>C. The results display</para>
      </listitem>

     </orderedlist>
   </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   
 </section>

  <section>
      <title>A. The class chooser page</title>
        <itemizedlist>

            <listitem>
              <para>The screen shot below shows the class
              chooser. This displays only the main starting points for
              a query and these have been divided into biologically
              meaniful categories.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="classSelection2.png" />
              </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Class Selection</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>

         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>In addition to the above classes a full list of
            classes from which you can start your query can be
            accessed by clicking on the 'List all classes' link (see
            above screenshot). This takes you to the class chooser
            page (see screenshot below). This page contains a list of
            classes for which objects exist in the database
            (i.e. classes for which there is data associated)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Selecting the class from which you wish to start your query
            and pressing the 'Select' button will take you to the FlyMine
            query builder page.</para>
          </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>          
  
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../tutorials/classSelection1.png" />
            </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Class Selection</phrase></textobject>
          </mediaobject>

        <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>The browse model button (accessed from the initial class
            selection point)allows you to browse the complete FlyMine
            object model. This shows all the classes in FlyMine, some
            of which do not yet have data associated with them.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In browse mode, the number on the right shows the number of
            objects associated with that class.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Clicking on a class name within the browser will take you to
            the FlyMine query builder page.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
     </section>

   <section>
        <title>B. The main query builder page</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>The main FlyMine query builder page is composed
        of 3 sections (shown in the screen shot below):</para>
           
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>a model browser (left)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a constraints list (right)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>an output fields list (bottom)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="queryBuilder1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Query Builder</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

         <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The model browser</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The model browser allows you to select the classes that
                contain the objects you require. Depending on the starting
                class you will be able to navigate to other classes as defined
                by the references between the classes (see <ulink
                url="manualCOF.xml">Classes, objects and fields</ulink> for an
                explanation of these concepts). In other words, to combine
                classes containing the objects you require, you find a path
                through the classes that link together the information you
                require. Within the model browser classes that can be accessed
                from a parent class (ie are linked to the parent class through
                a reference) are shown as fields within that class.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>For each class and field within the model browser there
                is a 'show' and a 'constrain' (-&gt;) option. These are used
                to either select a field to show in the results output or to
                constrain in the constraints list.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>See <ulink url="manualModelbrowser.xml">The model
                browser</ulink> for more information about classes and
                fields.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="modelBrowser2.png" />
              </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Model Browser</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The constraints list</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The constraints list is on the right hand side of the
                query builder page. In this section you specify the
                constraints you wish to apply to particular classes and
                fields.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>To apply a constraint to a field, navigate to the field
                in the model browser and click on the -&gt; (constrain) next
                to it. This will add the field to the constraints list and
                bring up a box in which you specify your constraint.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The type of constraint you can add will vary depending
                on the type of field you selected to constrain.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="constraintsList1.png" />
              </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Constraints List</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The output fields list</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The output fields list is located at the bottom of the
                query builder (underneath the Model browser). Initially the
                output fields list will say 'No fields selected for
                output'.</para>

                <para>The output fields list shows all fields or classes that
                you have selected to show in the results output. To select a
                field to show in the results output you press 'show' next to
                the field or class.</para>

                <para>The order of fields and classes in the output fields
                list can be changed using the &lt; and &gt; arrows. Fields can
                be deleted from the output fields list using the x.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="fieldsSelected1.png" />
              </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Fields Selected</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>

          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
     
</section>

<section>
   
        <title>C. The Results page</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The results page displays the first 10 objects returned by
            your query.</para>

            <para>The number of objects displayed can be changed by changing
            the number in the Page size box and pressing Change.</para>

            <para>You can scroll though the objects using Next, or go to the
            last 10 objects using Last.</para>

            <para>The total number of objects returned by your query is
            estimated. An estimate is given because, for large queries, only a
            subset of the total number of objects is initially returned by the
            query. This is to improve query run time for large queries.</para>

            <para>From the results page you can save your data to a bag (see
            <ulink url="manualSavingdata.xml">Saving bags of data</ulink>) and
            export your data in various formats (see <ulink
            url="manualExportingdata.xml">Exporting data</ulink>).</para>

            <para>If there are any objects in your results (rather than
            fields) you can click on an object to view it in detail.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../tutorials/resultsQuery1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Results Query</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
     
  </section>


<section>
   
        <title>D. Attribute List vs Browse Mode: 2 modes of result display</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>There are two modes of result display in FlyMine depending on whether you select attributes of classes to show or an entire Class.  This is illustrated in the screenshot below.  It is also possible to show a mix of attributes and objects in the result display.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>



        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="modelBrowser_browsing1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Browsing</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>



        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Selecting attributes results in a table-style results output as shown in the results displayed in the screenshot above.  Selecting a class to 'show' in the results output means that each object required from that class will be returned. For each object in the database there is a detailed results view which shows all the attributes of the objects and the classes referenced by that object.  From this detailed results view it is possible to browse the information contained in the referenced classes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>



       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resultsDetails1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase>Results Details</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>




</section>

</article>
