<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Predefined queries</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To provide a more direct route to the data in FlyMine, a
        number of queries have been predefined as templates.  A
        template query is like a form with various boxes for you to
        fill in. A number of template queries have been
        predefined. These range from simple queries to more complex
        queries covering a wide range of data.  </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         <para>Template queries can be accessed from the main FlyMine
         query page.  Templates can be selected either via a link from
         the class categories section, where the templates have also
         been divided into appropriate biological categories (note
         that a template query may belong in more than category) or
         from the 'Predefined template queries' section on the main query
         page, from where there is a link to all template
         queries (see screenshot below).</para>
      </listitem>

       <listitem>
           <para>To run a template query:</para>
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>


 <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>Select the query you wish to run either from the
           lists on the main Query page or by selecting 'view all
           template queries'.  Pressing the -&gt; next to the query
           description will take you to the template form.</para>

      <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="templates1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

</listitem>



         <listitem>
           <para>Fill in the boxes with the appropriate values or
           leave them with the default values shown (see screenshot
           below).</para>
         </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>Pressing the 'View results' button will take you
           directly to the results page (see <ulink
           url="manualResultdisplay.xml">The result page</ulink> for
           more details). Pressing the 'View query' button will
           display the template query in the FlyMine Query Builder.
           Here you can either use the template as a starting point
           for building a more complex query, edit the query or simply
           run the query as it is.  Press 'Show results' to run your
           query. See <ulink url="manualStartingquery.xml">The FlyMine
           query builder</ulink> for more details.</para>
        


      <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="templates2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

      </listitem>

       </orderedlist>

</section>

</article>
 


 
