<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>The model browser</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The FlyMine model browser allows you to select the classes that
        contain the objects you require. Depending on the starting class you
        will be able to navigate to other classes as defined by the references
        between the classes (see <ulink url="manualCOF.xml">Classes, objects
        and fields</ulink> for an explanation of these concepts). In other
        words, to combine classes containing the objects you require, you find
        a path through the classes that link together the information you
        require. Within the model browser classes that can be accessed from a
        parent class (ie are linked to the parent class through a reference)
        are shown as fields within that class.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For each class and field within the model browser there is a
        'show' and a 'constrain' (-&gt;) option. These are used to either
        select a field to show in the results output or to constrain in the
        constraints list.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="modelBrowser1.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fields</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following is an explanation of the classes and fields
        displayed by the model browser. The Gene class is used as an example,
        but the information is easily transferable to other classes. The
        screen-shot below shows the model browser displaying the Gene
        class.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The following fields are of the type 'String': name, residues
        and wormBaseSequenceName. These fields hold just one piece of
        information of the type String. A String is basically a piece of text
        that can include letters and numbers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The field called Organism is a reference (ie a link) to the
        organism class. Fields which are references to other classes have a
        field name (in this case organism) followed by the name of the class
        it is referencing (in this case Organism).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The field called Transcript is also a reference to a class - the
        Transcript class. This field, however, also has the type 'collection'.
        This is because a particular gene object in the Gene class will
        reference (link to) one or more transcript objects in the Transcripts
        class. The transcript collection is a list of references to these
        transcript objects.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The other fields in the gene class are all of the type class
        collection as described above.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="fields1.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</article>