<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>StemCellMine is an open-source project to build an integrated data warehouse for Stem Cell projects as part of the CMI Systems Biology KIC.</para> 
 

 <para>Currently, biological data is stored in a wide variety of formats in numerous different places, making complex queries across these data sources very difficult. In addition it is often possible to make stronger inferences when data are combined and analysed together. One of the current challenges for bioinformatics is therefore to develop resources for the integration and combined analysis of such data.</para>

 <para>StemCellMine is built on <ulink url="http://www.intermine.org">InterMine</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.flymine.org">FlyMine</ulink>.  <ulink url="http://www.intermine.org">InterMine</ulink> is a general purpose object-oriented data warehouse system developed as part of the FlyMine project. <ulink url="http://www.flymine.org">FlyMine</ulink> is built using InterMine with primary focus on Drosophila, Anopheles and other insects. StemCellMine is adapting the <ulink url="http://www.flymine.org">FlyMine</ulink> data integration architecture to integrate genomics, genetics and protein data from human, mouse and rat as part of efforts to study stem cell. Currently we have integrated the Ensembl human genome annotation, GO annotation, FirstEF, Transfac binding sites and Encode regions from UCSC and TFBinding Sites and TFBSclusters from <ulink url="http://hscl.cimr.cam.ac.uk">HSCL</ulink>(Transcriptional Networks in Haematopoietic Stem Cells and Leukaemia Laboratory). These have been merged with the sequence ontology data model into a single query-optimised object database. Users are able to create complex, powerful, arbitrary queries on the integrated data via an intuitive web application or access the data via simpler predefined template queries.</para>

 <para>StemCellMine is in continuous development and please check <ulink url="techdesc.xml">technical desciption</ulink> for further details.</para>
</section>
</article>


