<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?> 
<article>
  <section>
    <title>What can I do with StemCellMine?</title>
    <para>
        StemCellMine is an integrated database of genomic, expression and protein data for
        <emphasis>Homo sapiens</emphasis>, <emphasis>Mus musculus</emphasis>, 
        <emphasis>Monodelphis domestica</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>Canis familiaris</emphasis> with emphasize on <emphasis>Stem Cell</emphasis> research.
        Integrating data makes it possible to run sophisticated data mining queries
        that span domains of biological knowledge.      
    </para>
    
    <verbatim><h3>Quick Search</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      Enter any identifier or symbol in the search box on the StemCellMine
      home page to access summary pages and integrated tools.  See FlyMine webpage for
     <ulink url="/doc/tutorials/quickSearch.xml">Tutorial 1</ulink> 
     <ulink url="/doc/tutorials/objectDetails.xml">Tutorial 2</ulink>. 
    </para>

    <para>Some examples:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>for the <emphasis>Homo sapiens</emphasis> gene, type
        <ulink url="http://www.ensembl.org/Homo_sapiens/index.html">Ensembl</ulink> identifiers (eg. ENSG00000186445),
        <ulink url="http://www.gene.ucl.ac.uk/cgi-bin/nomenclature/searchgenes.pl">HUGO</ulink> identifiers, (eg. 29997), 
         or any of its synonyms.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>for proteins use <ulink url="http://www.uniprot.org">UniProt</ulink> identifiers or primary accessions (eg. COX1_HUMAN, P00395).</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
        
    <verbatim><h3>Browse Aspects</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      StemCellMine presents data as 'aspects', with each aspect providing a
      'view' of a particular type of data (for example Gene Expression
      or Protein Interactions). Use the aspect icons on the StemCellMine
      home page to run a predefined template query or to build your
      own query (see below). Certain template queries, as well as the
      QueryBuilder itself, allow you to perform searches that span
      more than one aspect.
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>Run Template Queries</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      A number of specific queries have been predefined. These template queries range from 
      fairly simple queries to retrieve a particular type of data to more complex queries that 
      span the different types of data availbale in StemCellMine. More template queries will be added 
      as StemCellMine develops and we welcome suggestions. Find lists of predefined template 
      queries on each aspect page or use the Template Search box on the StemCellMine home page 
      and in the top menu on every page. 
      <ulink url="/doc/tutorials/templates.xml">Tutorial 3</ulink>
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>StemCellMine QueryBuilder</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      Advanced users can use a flexible query interface to construct
      their own data mining queries across the multiple integrated
      data sources, to modify existing template queries or to create
      your own template queries. Access the StemCellMine QueryBuilder via
      the StemCellMine home page or choose a query starting point on an
      aspect page.
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>Operate on Lists</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      All queries in StemCellMine can be performed on lists (or
      '<emphasis>bags</emphasis>') that you create yourself. Bags can
      be created by typing or pasting in a list of identifiers, or
      uploading a file containing the list. Data from previous queries
      can also be saved into a bag using the boxes displayed
      underneath the query results. Saved bags of data can be used to
      constrain new queries, perform logical operations and can be
      exported.
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>Save Queries</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      You can save your bags, queries and templates between sessions by
      <ulink url="/login.do">creating an account</ulink> using the 'Log in' box
      in the top menu on every page.
    </para>

    <verbatim><br/></verbatim>
    <verbatim><br/></verbatim>

    <para>
      See flymine webpage for <ulink url="/doc/tutorials/index.xml">short tutorials</ulink> and 
      <ulink url="/doc/manual/index.xml">user manual</ulink> for more information.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
</article>

