<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article>

<artheader>
<date>2004-06-30</date>
<title>Obtaining software</title>
</artheader>

<para>In order to improve the chance of continued funding for the
InterMine project it would be really appreciated if anyone that uses
InterMine or parts of InterMine would let us know. Just drop a quick email
to <email>info[at]intermine.org</email>.</para>

<para>InterMine is open-source software, available for download and
use under the terms of the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html">
GNU LGPL licence</ulink>.</para>

<para>The source code can be obtained via a download, or via anonymous
CVS.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Downloading the source code</title>

<para>The source code can be downloaded as either an official release,
or a nightly build. You will find files starting from intermine-src, intermine-tutorial and flymine-src, they are intermine source code, intermine tutorial source code and flymine source code respectively. You can download depending on your needs.</para>
<para>The source code is available in tar.gz or ZIP format.</para>

<para><ulink
url="http://download.flymine.org/releases/">Official releases</ulink> -
this is where the official InterMine release appear. Official releases are planned to occur 
every couple of months, on average.</para>

<para><ulink
url="http://download.flymine.org/nightly/">Nightly build</ulink> - this
is a snapshot of the InterMine source code taken last night. This will work, but may be in a state of flux, and with
portions undocumented, or not conforming to the documentation.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Obtaining source code via anonymous CVS access</title>

<para>Anonymous CVS access to the InterMine source code is via our
public CVS server, cvs.flymine.org. This server contains a read-only
snapshot of the CVS source the software developers are using, updated
every 10 minutes.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Instructions</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><command>cd</command> to the directory into which you intend
to check out the source.</listitem>

<listitem>Issue the command <command>cvs -d
:pserver:anonymous@cvs.flymine.org:/cvs
login</command>. No password is needed.</listitem>

<listitem>Then type <command>cvs -d
:pserver:anonymous@cvs.flymine.org:/cvs co
intermine</command>.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<para>Once you have checked out the source from the CVS server, the
command <command>cvs update</command> will obtain any updates to the
code made by the development team. You should issue this command
regularly.</para>


</sect1>

</article>

