<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>How to build and run the tutorial</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>The tutorial consists of a simple model in ArgoUML format, some test
  data for this model and a Java program to query the data. It includes the
  InterMine jar, its dependencies, the necessary configuration files and a
  build script.</para>

  <para>Building the tutorial involves a few simple steps:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Ensure that you have the <ulink url="prerequisites.xml">required
      software</ulink> installed, including Tomcat.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url="http://download.flymine.org/nightly/">Download</ulink>
      and unpack the latest InterMine tutorial
      (intermine-tutorial-xxxxxxxx).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Change to the tutorial root directory, modify the
      <filename>intermine.properties</filename> configuration file to reflect
      your database server name, database user name, and password if
      necessary. Note that you must run <command>createdb tutorial</command>
      before attempting to store data.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Depending on your requirements there is a choice of targets that
      you can run. Issue the command <command> ant help</command> to display
      user targets or <command>ant -projecthelp</command> for a full target
      list. <command>ant run</command> will read and store the data, and
      perform a query to ensure it was stored correctly. The source
      (<filename>src/java/org/intermine/tutorial/SimpleQuery.java</filename>)
      demonstrates how this query is run for the model
      (<filename>model/tutorial/tutorial.zargo</filename>). The results, can
      be compared to the test data
      (<filename>resources/tutorial_data.xml</filename>).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>If you wish to deploy the web front-end for the tutorial model
      then first modify the <filename>build.properties</filename>
      configuration file ensuring the destination server and path are correct.
      Then run the <command>ant release-webapp</command> command to release
      the tutorial web application to the server.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</article>