<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>

<para>The FlyMine project is building an integrated database of genomic, expression and protein data for
<firstterm>Drosophila</firstterm> and <firstterm>Anopheles</firstterm> and making this available to the worldwide research community via web and bioinformatics interfaces. The FlyMine project is based at the
<ulink url="http://www.gen.cam.ac.uk">Department of Genetics</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://www.cam.ac.uk">University of Cambridge</ulink> and is a collaboration between the Genetics and <ulink url="http://www.bioc.cam.ac.uk">Biochemistry</ulink> departments of the University of Cambridge.</para>

<index>
    <section>
        <heading>Main aims of the project</heading>
        <item>To create a database for the management of Drosophila and Anopheles data generated by existing high-throughput post-genomics techniques: expression studies, proteomics and 3D protein structure prediction.</item>

        <item>To integrate the above database with the curated database of Drosophila genetics (FlyBase), the annotated view of the Drosophila genome (GadFly) and corresponding Anopheles data.</item>

        <item>To enable the database to be queried via the Internet in order to facilitate the widest possible use by the broader community.</item>

        <item>To support bulk access to the data for those studying the entire dataset and for those generating new analysis algorithms.</item>

        <item>To provide information that will allow other resources to link to the contents of the database.</item>

        <item>To make the database schema and associated programs freely available to the community using an open source CVS repository. Likewise to work collaboratively to generate and promote the use of public data exchange standards.</item>

        <item>To provide analysis support to facilitate use of the database and data by the community.</item>
    </section>

    <section>
        <heading>More information</heading>
        <item><ulink url="team.xml">About the team</ulink></item>
        <item><ulink url="funding.xml">About the funding</ulink></item>
        <item><ulink url="jobs.xml">Potiential job opportunities</ulink></item>
    </section>
</index>
</article>
