<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <para>The FlyMine project is building an integrated database of genomic,
  expression and protein data for <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> and
  <emphasis>Anopheles</emphasis> and making this available to the worldwide
  research community via web and bioinformatics interfaces. The FlyMine
  project is based at the <ulink url="http://www.sysbiol.cam.ac.uk/">Systems
  Biology Centre</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.cam.ac.uk/">University of
  Cambridge</ulink> and is a collaboration between the
  <ulink url="http://www.gen.cam.ac.uk/">Genetics</ulink> and
  <ulink url="http://www.bioc.cam.ac.uk/">Biochemistry</ulink>
  departments of the University of Cambridge.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Main aims of the project</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To create a database for the management of Drosophila and
        Anopheles data generated by existing high-throughput post-genomics
        techniques: expression studies, proteomics and 3D protein structure
        prediction.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To integrate the above database with the curated database of
        Drosophila genetics (FlyBase), the annotated view of the Drosophila
        genome (GadFly) and corresponding Anopheles data.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To enable the database to be queried via the Internet in order
        to facilitate the widest possible use by the broader community.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To support bulk access to the data for those studying the entire
        dataset and for those generating new analysis algorithms.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To provide information that will allow other resources to link
        to the contents of the database.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To make the database schema and associated programs freely
        available to the community using an open source CVS repository.
        Likewise to work collaboratively to generate and promote the use of
        public data exchange standards.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To provide analysis support to facilitate use of the database
        and data by the community.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>More information</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="team.xml">About the team</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="funding.xml">About the funding</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="jobs.xml">Potential job opportunities</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>
