<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->

<article>
<sect1>
<title>Positions vacant</title>

<para>
The following positions are currently vacant on the FlyMine project
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Computer Officer Grade II (Software Development)</title>

<para>Salary: GBP 29,478 - GBP 31,715pa</para>
<para>Limit of tenure: 30 April 2005 *</para>

<para>We are looking for a software developer, ideally with experience in a biological field to join a Wellcome Trust funded project that seeks to integrate functional genomics data from the model organisms Drosophila melanogaster and Anopheles gambiae, using data generated by high throughput laboratory activity in the department and worldwide.</para>

<para>We are building a web application and associated infrastructure that will enable researchers to perform complex queries over a wide range of genomic and proteomic data sources, containing many terabytes of data between them. We are using Java and XML with a PostgreSQL backend, in a Linux/Unix environment, and making use of existing open source tools and libraries where possible. All our code is freely available under an open source licence. As a team, the software developers are responsible for gathering requirements, designing, coding and testing the system, many parts of which are technically challenging. Further details of the project can be found at <ulink url="http://www.flymine.org">www.flymine.org</ulink></para>

<para>You will be heavily involved with all aspects of the system, including design, data, data model and dataflow. Ideally you should have a background in the computational or engineering sciences and we would expect you to have over 1 years experience in small team java software/ database development. Experience with SQL/ OQL, XML and ontologies would be a strong advantage.</para>

<para>* Funds for this post are available until 30 April 2005 in the first instance, and the post may, subject to availability of funding, be renewed for a further period or periods.</para>

<para>Informal enquiries to Richard Smith: <email>richard@flymine.org</email>.</para>

<para> Applications, to include a <ulink url="http://www.admin.cam.ac.uk/offices/personnel/forms/pd18/">PD18</ulink> cover sheet, full CV and details of three referees, should be addressed to Mrs Tracy Oakley, Department of Genetics, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, Cambridge, CB2 3EH, tel: (01223) 333 999, e-mail: <email>t.oakley@gen.cam.ac.uk</email></para> 

<para>Closing date: 16 August 2004.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
