<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->

<article>
<sect1>
<title>Positions vacant</title>

<para>
The following positions are currently vacant on the FlyMine project
</para>

<sect2>

<title>Computer Officer Grade II (Software Development)</title>

<para>Salary: £28,498 - £30,660</para>
<para>Limit of tenure: 30 April 2005 *</para>

<para>We are looking for a software developer with a background in
biology to join a small team working on a project that seeks to
integrate functional genomics data from the model organisms Drosophila
melanogaster and Anopheles gambiae, using data generated by high
throughput laboratory activity in the department and worldwide.</para>

<para>We are building a web application and associated infrastructure
that will enable researchers to perform complex queries over a wide
range of genomic and proteomic data sources, containing many terabytes
of data between them. We are using Java and XML with a PostgreSQL
backend, in a Linux/Unix environment, and making use of existing open
source tools and libraries where possible. All our code is freely
available under an open source licence. As a team, the software
developers are responsible for gathering requirements, designing,
coding and testing the system, many parts of which are technically
challenging.  Further details of the project can be found at
<ulink url="http://www.flymine.org"/>.</para>

<para>You will be heavily involved with the data, data model and
dataflow aspects of the system.   You should have a background in the
biological sciences and be familiar with biological data sources and
the modelling and analysis of biological data, including the use of
ontologies. You should also have at least one year's experience of
software development in Java and any experience in using XML or
SQL/OQL would be an advantage.</para>

<para>* Funds for this post are available until 30 April 2005 in the
first instance, and the post may, subject to availability of funding,
be renewed for a further period or periods.</para>

<para>Informal enquiries to Dr. Andrew Varley:
<email>ajv12@cam.ac.uk</email>.  Applications, to include a PD18 cover
sheet, full CV and details of three referees, should be addressed to
Miss Marie Chambers, Department of Genetics, University of Cambridge,
Downing Street, Cambridge, CB2 3EH, tel: (01223) 333 999, e-mail:
<email>mc371@gen.cam.ac.uk</email>.</para>

<para>The closing date for applications is 31 October 2003.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
