<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
<title>Job Opportunities</title>

  <para>Part-time Maternity Cover. FlyMine Project: Biologist - Database analysis and user support.
</para>

  <para>A maternity cover position has become available within the FlyMine
project and is available on a part-time basis.</para>

  <para>FlyMine (http://www.flymine.org) is an open source project being
developed in the Department of Genetics to build an integrated
database of genomic, gene expression and protein data for Drosophila,
Anopheles and other insects.  Currently such data are available from
disparate sources in many different formats making querying across
them difficult.  The aim of FlyMine is to incorporate much of these
data into a single, integrated database and make it available online.
A sophisticated web appliction permits researchers to construct
arbitrary, complex queries across the data allowing comparisons and
inferences to be made.  Access is also possible using a library of
pre-defined 'template' queries and browsable reports.

</para>

  <para>We seek a proactive, experienced biologist to join the team as
maternity cover. The position requires working closely with software
developers and supporting end-users.</para>

 <para>Key areas of work include:
 </para>
 <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
        <listitem>
           <para>
* Biological support for the software developers - providing information about data
sources to be loaded and how they should be modelled in a biologically intuitive way.
</para>
 </listitem>
        <listitem>
<para>* Analysis of the modelled data and advising on new user interface features</para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>
* Expanding the library of pre-defined queries to take full advantage of the 
integrated data
           </para>
       </listitem>
        <listitem>
           <para>
* Providing documents and training for end-users in the form of a user manual, 
tutorials and running workshops locally and at conferences.
           </para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>
* Working with users to make sure they are able to extract the information they
require and assisting them with analysis of data.
           </para>
       </listitem>
        <listitem>
           <para>
* Providing feedback to the sofware developers about usage and data requirements,
and helping to set development priorities.
           </para>
       </listitem>
</orderedlist>


<para>The successful candidate is likely to have:
</para>

 <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
        <listitem>
           <para>
* A PhD in a biological field
           </para>
       </listitem>
        <listitem>
           <para>
* Broad knowledge of genomics, proteomics and current high-throughput
  biological techniques
           </para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>
* Worked on post-genomic biological data in a bioinformatics environment
           </para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>
* Experience in extracting information from biological databases
           </para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>
* Interest in data modelling for biological databases
           </para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>
* Familiarity with biological ontologies and data standards (e.g. SO, GO, MAGE, PSI)
           </para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>
* Some programming experience (particularly in Perl or Java)
           </para>
       </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
In addition, experience in Drosophila biology would be an advantage but is not essential.
</para>




  <para>Informal enquiries to Rachel Lyne <email>rachel[at]flymine.org</email></para>

  <para>No contact from agencies please.</para>

  <para>Applications, to include a <ulink url="http://www.admin.cam.ac.uk/offices/personnel/forms/pd18/">PD18</ulink> cover sheet, full CV and details of three referees, should be addressed to Mrs Tracy Oakley, Department of Genetics, Downing Street, Cambridge, CB2 3EH or e-mail: <email>t.oakley[at]gen.cam.ac.uk.</email></para>

  <para></para>

  <para>Closing date: 27 November 2006.</para>
  </section>
</article>


