<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article>

<artheader>
<date>2003-04-17</date>
<title>Downloading and building FlyMine</title>
</artheader>


<para>Depending on your needs, you can either download precompiled jar
files of the FlyMine distribution, or build these yourself from
source.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Obtaining the source code</title>

<para>The source code can be obtained via a download, or via anonymous
CVS.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Downloading the source code</title>

<para>The source code or a jar file containing precompiled classes can
be downloaded as either an official release, or a nightly
snapshot. The source code is available in tar.gz or ZIP
format.</para>

<para><ulink
url="http://download.flymine.org/releases/"><inlinegraphic
fileref="/images/download" align="center"/>Official releases</ulink> -
these are the official FlyMine releases. Official releases happen
every couple of months, on average.</para>

<para><ulink
url="http://download.flymine.org/nightly/"><inlinegraphic
fileref="/images/download" align="center"/>Nightly dump</ulink> - this
is an up-to-the-minute snapshot of the FlyMine source code, as it was
last night. This will work, but may be in a state of flux, and with
portions undocumented, or not conforming to the documentation.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Anonymous CVS access</title>

<para>The latest version of the FlyMine source code can be downloaded
anonymously from our CVS server using the following commands:</para>

<para><command>cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.flymine.org:/cvs login</command></para>

<para><command>Password: &lt;none&gt;</command></para>
<para><command>cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.flymine.org:/cvs co flymine</command></para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Building FlyMine</title>

<para>The only pre-requisite for building FlyMine is <ulink
url="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</ulink>. This should be downloaded and
installed on your machine.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Building a FlyMine client</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Issue the command <command>ant jar</command> (if building
from source). This will create a file <filename>flymine.jar</filename>
in the <filename>dist</filename> directory.</listitem>

<listitem>Copy the file <filename>flymine.jar</filename> to
a directory on your classpath</listitem>

<listitem>Write a program using the FlyMine Query API! This will
automatically contact the main FlyMine servers. Many things are
configurable by having a file <filename>flymine.properties</filename>
in your classpath (earlier than <filename>flymine.jar</filename>). An
example <filename>flymine.properties</filename> can be found in the
jar file.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Building a FlyMine server</title>

<para>FlyMine defines a number of datasources which are used during
building of the integrated database. These need to be installed
locally in order to be used.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Edit the file <filename>flymine.properties</filename>,
changing the locations of servers and datasources to match your local
site. This file is commented so should be
self-explainatory.</listitem>

<listitem>Issue the command <command>ant build-db</command> to build
the integrated database. This may take a very long time to complete,
depending on the number of datasources configured.</listitem>

<listitem>More here when this is done.......</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</article>
