<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article>

<artheader>
<date>2003-04-17</date>
<title>Downloading and building FlyMine</title>
</artheader>

<para>In order to improve the chance of continued funding for the
FlyMine project it would be really appreciated if anyone that uses
FlyMine or parts of FlyMine would let us know. Just drop a quick email
to <email>info[at]flymine.org</email>.</para>

<para>Depending on your needs, you can either download precompiled jar
files of the FlyMine distribution, or build these yourself from
source.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Obtaining the source code</title>

<para>The source code can be obtained via a download, or via anonymous
CVS.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Downloading the source code</title>

<para>The source code can be downloaded as either an official release,
or a nightly build. The source code is available in tar.gz or ZIP
format.</para>

<para><ulink
url="http://download.flymine.org/releases/">Official releases</ulink> -
this is where the official FlyMine release appear. Official releases are planned to occur 
every couple of months, on average.</para>

<para><ulink
url="http://download.flymine.org/nightly/">Nightly build</ulink> - this
is a snapshot of the FlyMine source code taken last night. This will work, but may be in a state of flux, and with
portions undocumented, or not conforming to the documentation.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Anonymous CVS access</title>

<para>Instructions can be found <ulink url="cvs-user">here</ulink>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Building FlyMine from the source code</title>

<para>The only prerequisite for building FlyMine is <ulink
url="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</ulink>. This should be downloaded and
installed on your machine.</para>

<para>Depending on your requirements there are a choice of targets
that you can build.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Building a FlyMine client</title>

<para>A FlyMine client is simply a program that accesses the FlyMine
data, the data being on a local machine, or accessed via a FlyMine
webservice.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Issue the command <command>ant jar</command> (if building
from source). This will create a file <filename>flymine.jar</filename>
in the <filename>dist</filename> directory.</listitem>

<listitem>Copy the file <filename>flymine.jar</filename> to
a directory on your classpath</listitem>

<listitem>Copy any of the jars in the <filename>lib/</filename>
directory that you don't already have to a directory on your
classpath</listitem>

<listitem>Write a program using the FlyMine Query API. Many things
(such as locations of the data) are configurable by having a file
<filename>flymine.properties</filename> in your classpath (earlier
than <filename>flymine.jar</filename>). An example
<filename>flymine.properties</filename> can be found in the jar
file.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Building a FlyMine database</title>

<para>A FlyMine database contains data in a certain format that has
been integrated from various other data sources. These data sources
must be installed locally and their locations configures in
<filename>flymine.properties</filename>.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Edit the file <filename>flymine.properties</filename>,
changing the locations of servers and datasources to match your local
site. This file is commented so should be
self-explanatory.</listitem>

<listitem>Issue the command <command>ant build-db</command> to build
the integrated database. This may take a very long time to complete,
depending on the number of datasources configured.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Building a FlyMine web site</title>

<para>A FlyMine website is the front end to a FlyMine ObjectStore.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Ensure you have an running Tomcat installation, including
the manager application.</listitem>

<listitem>Configure the webserver properties in the
<filename>build.properties</filename> file.</listitem>

<listitem>Configure the underlying ObjectStore properties in the
<filename>flymine.properties</filename> file.</listitem>

<listitem>Issue the command <command>ant release-webapp</command>.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>


<sect2>
<title>Building a FlyMine web service</title>

<para>A FlyMine webservice provides SOAP access to an underlying ObjectStore.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Ensure you have an running Tomcat installation, including
the manager application.</listitem>

<listitem>Configure the webserver properties in the
<filename>build.properties</filename> file.</listitem>

<listitem>Configure the underlying ObjectStore properties in the
<filename>flymine.properties</filename> file.</listitem>

<listitem>Issue the command <command>ant release-webservice</command>.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</article>
