<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial 2: <emphasis>Navigating object details pages</emphasis></title>

    <para>This tutorial will guide you through the structure of the
    object details pages and how to navigate them.  The object details
    page for the 'bib' gene will be used as an example.  All object
    details pages have the same basic structure and so this example
    can be extended to other items in the database.</para>

    <para>Enter the gene symbol 'bib' into the Quick Search box on the
    FlyMine home page. See <ulink url="quickSearch.xml">Tutorial 1</ulink>
    for more information. The query returns just one result so you are taken
    directly to a summary page for the gene:</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetailsTop.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>


    <para>The top left shows summary information for this gene - identifier, name
    and chromosome coordinates.  Use the '+' boxes next to 'proteins', 'synonyms',
    etc. to open inline tables with more details.  The 'FASTA' buttons retrieve
    sequences for any feature they appear next to.</para>

    <para>The top right presents:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>A link to the FlyBase gene report.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>A GBrowse image for the area surrounding this gene.  Clicking
      on the image takes you to the GBrowse genome viewer.  Clicking on any feature
      in GBrowse will take you to a summary page in FlyMine.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>'bib' has results from the Arbeitman et al 2002 time course
      microarray experiment.  The graph shows Log 2 Ratio gene expression for
      67 samples.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Scroll down the page to see 'Other details by aspect':</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetailsAspects.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
 
    <para>This section has more detailed information about this gene
    divided into 'aspects'. The aspects correspond to categories of
    data shown on the FlyMine home page.  Look at the Genomics aspect.
    Entries in green show fields directly related to this gene. Use
    '+' boxes to open summary tables. For example, opening
    'overlappingFeatures' will summarise genome annotation that
    overlaps the chromosome coordinates of this gene.</para>

    <para>Entries in black text allow you to see the results of predefined
    queries run for this gene ('templates'). Those shown in light grey did
    not return any results.</para>

    <para>[details...] links take you to summary pages for related database
    entries.  Scroll back up to the top of the page and click the [details...]
    link next to 'proteins':</para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="objectDetailsProtein.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>This page presents more information about the 'BIB_DROME' protein.
    The trail at the top keeps track of [details...] links you have followed.</para>

  </section>
</article>
