<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial3: <emphasis>Show all the orthologues between
    <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis> and <emphasis>Anopheles
    gambiae</emphasis></emphasis></title>

    <para>This page will guide you through the query: Show all the
    orthologues between <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis>. The aim of this
    query tutorial is to show you how a 'relation' between two
    BioEntity objects (eg genes) is linked via a subject and an
    object. This query involves:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Selecting the Orthologue class.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Constraining the objects of the relation to
        <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis> and constraining
        the subjects of the relation to <emphasis>Caenorhabditis
        elegans</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the starting point for your query. Navigate to
        the 'Comparative genomics' aspect and select 'Orthologue' from
        the 'Query starting points'.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="query3_1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The model browser will now be displaying the Orthologue
        class and it's fields. The Orthologue class is a subclass
        (specialisation) of the Relation class. The Relation class
        links two BioEntity objects that have some type of
        relationship with each other. Every relation has a subject and
        an object. If two genes are orthologues, one of the genes will
        be the subject of the relation and the other the object.  You
        need to add constraints to specify that you want the objects
        of the orthologue relation to be BioEntity objects (in this
        case genes) from <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis>
        and the subjects of the relation to be BioEntity objects from
        <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis>. 
       </para>

        <para>
        The Relation class has the three fields: evidence, object and
        subject. Expand the object field. The object field has a link
        (reference) to the Organism class. Expand the organism class.
        Click on the constrain arrow next to the name field of the
        Organism class and add the constraint '= Drosophila
        melanogaster'. Click on 'Add to query' to add this to the
        constraints list. In the same way, constrain the Organism name
        field of the subject to '= Caenorhabditis elegans'</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="query3_2.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You want to display the identifier of the object and the subject
        in your results. In this case the object and the subject are genes, so
        the identifier fields will refer to the gene's main identifier. Select
        the identifier fields of the object and the subject to show in the
        results.</para>

      <para>[Alternatively, select 'show' next to the 'object
      BioEntity' and 'subject BioEntity' class names to create a table
      of browsable object summaries.]
      </para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="query3_3.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Press 'Show results' to view your results in the results
        page:</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="query3_4.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</article>
