<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <section>
    <title>Tutorial 8: MyMine</title>



    <para>It is possible to save bags, queries and templates
    permanently to FlyMine, in a personal FlyMine account called
    MyMine, by creating a log-in.  Your MyMine account allows you to
    manage your saved items.  To create a log-in, click on 'Log in' on
    the main menu bar at the top of each FlyMine page, and give an
    email address and password. To access your MyMine account click on
    'MyMine' on the top menu bar.</para>


    <para>Your MyMine page has four tabs: Bags, Saved queries, Saved
    templates and Favourite templates plus a tab to allow you to
    change your password.</para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="MyMine1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

    <para>In this tutorial we will look at how to save queries. See
   <ulink url="tutorial4-Bags.xml">Tutorial 4</ulink> for information
   on how to save bags and <ulink url="tutorial7-Export.xml">Tutorial
   7</ulink> for information on how to build and save your own
   template queries.</para>

    
    <para>Every query that is run in FlyMine (template queries and
    queries constructed in the query builder, but not quick search
    queries) is automatically saved with a default name (format
    query_x (x=incrementing number).  These are saved to your query
    history. </para>

    <para> Find the template 'Gene --> Orthologues' under the
    'Comparative genomics' aspect. Run this template with the default
    values provided.  At the top of the results page notice that there
    is a message saying 'Saved in your query history as "query_x"'.
    You can access your query history from the top menu bar.</para>

    
      <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="MyMine2.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

 
     <para>Your 'Query history' lists all the queries you have run in
     this particular session and gives the date and time they were
     run, the starting class of the query and the fields in the
     results (these latter two columns are more relevent if you have
     constructed a query yourself in the query builder or modified a
     template in the query builder).  For each query there are also a
     set of actions: Run, Edit, Save and Export:</para>
   
    <orderedlist>

      <listitem>
	<para>Run: will run the query directly. </para></listitem>

       <listitem>
	<para>Edit: Will take you either to the template form if you
	ran a template query or to the query builder if you
	constructed the query yourself (or modified a
	template).</para> </listitem> 

       <listitem> 
       <para>Save: This allows you to save your query permanently to
	the 'Saved queries' tab of your MyMine
	account.</para></listitem>

       <listitem>
       <para>Export: This allows you to export the query as xml.  This
       is useful if you want to give your query to someone else to
       use in FlyMine (queries saved as xml can be re-imported into
       FlyMine).</para></listitem>

   </orderedlist>    


   
      <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="MyMine3.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>



    <para>Navigate to your query history, find the query you just ran
    and click on 'Save'.  You will automatically be taken to the
    'Saved queries' tab of your MyMine page where you can find your
    saved query.  Click on the blue circle next to the query name to
    re-name the query.  Note that queries can also be re-named in your
    query history. Queries saved in your MyMine account have the same
    set of actions available as for the query history described
    above.</para>

     <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="MyMine4.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>



    <para>Queries constructed in the query builder can be saved
    directly to your MyMine account.  At the bottom of the query
    builder page under 'Actions' is a box allowing you to name and
    save your query.  This option is only available if you are logged
    in.</para>



    <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="MyMine5.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>


 </section>
</article>
