
<article>
  <column width="60%">
    <section>
      <title>
        Introduction
      </title>
      
      <para>FlyMine is an integrated database of genomic, expression and protein data for <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> and <emphasis>Anopheles</emphasis>. Integrating data makes it possible to run sophisticated data mining queries that span domains of biological knowledge. Use <highlights>aspect</highlights> icons below to to find out more about types of data in FlyMine and to start queries.  Use FlyMine to:
      </para>
      <para>
        <highlights>Browse data -</highlights> Enter any identifier or symbol in the search box to the right to access summary pages and integrated tools.  [tutorial 1]
      </para>
      <para>
        <highlights>Run Template Queries -</highlights> A library of pre-defined ('template') queries that simply require filling in a form is available. Find lists of templates on each aspect page or using the Template Search box below.  [tutorial 2]
      </para>
      <para>
        <highlights>Operate on lists -</highlights> All queries in FlyMine can be performed on lists (or '<highlights>bags</highlights>').  For example, any query that operates on a single gene could use a list of gene identifiers you create yourself. [tutorial 3]
      </para>
      <para>
        <highlights>Design your own query -</highlights> Advanced users can use a flexible query interface to construct their own data mining queries or modify existing template queries. You can save queries for future use and create your own templates. See the [user manual] and [tutorials] for more information.
      </para>
      <!--
      <para>
        Full <ulink url="doc/index.xml">user documentation</ulink> is available. 
        For further information about FlyMine please consult the more detailed
        <ulink url="introduction.xml">introduction</ulink>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <ulink url="/begin.do">Start a query</ulink> using FlyMine.
        See <ulink url="doc/manual/quickStartGuide.xml">quick start guide</ulink>
        for more details.
      </para>
      -->
    </section>
  
  

  </column>
  
  <column width="39%">
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Browse by identifier
      </title>
      <para>Search for genes, proteins or any other annotation [help].</para>
      <para>
        <ssi-include page="browse.tile"/>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>
        FlyMine News:
      </title>
        <news id="news" limit="3"/> <!-- Source now defined in branding -->
        <ulink url="news.xml">All news...</ulink>
    </section>

  </column>

  <section clear="both">
    <title>
      Aspects
    </title>
    
    <para>Choose an aspect to explore the different types of data in FlyMine and start queries.</para>
    <!--
    <para>
      FlyMine is an application of <ulink url="http://www.intermine.org">InterMine</ulink>.
      Release 3.1 of FlyMine incorporates the following data sources:
    </para>
      <sources sources="/sources.xml" version="3.0"/>
    -->
    <ssi-include page="/aspectIcons.jsp&amp;cols=3"/>
    <things-to-do/>
  </section>

    
  
  <section clear="both">
    <title>
      Template search
    </title>
    <para>Templates are pre-defined queries that simply require filling in a form.  Find relevant templates on each of the aspects above or use the search box.  Example: enter 'orthologues GO'</para>
    <para>
      <template-search/>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  
  <section>
    <title>
      Funding and contact details
    </title>
    <para>
      The FlyMine project is based at the
      <ulink url="http://www.gen.cam.ac.uk">Department of Genetics</ulink>,
      <ulink url="http://www.cam.ac.uk">University of Cambridge</ulink> and is a
      collaboration between the Genetics and
      <ulink url="http://www.bioc.cam.ac.uk">Biochemistry</ulink> departments of the
      University of Cambridge.
    </para>
  </section>
  
</article>
