<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  
  <section>
    <title>What can I do with FlyMine?</title>
    
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Browse data. All entries in FlyMine have a summary page includes data from all aspects. Some example gene: ..... and protein pages..... Enter any identifier or symbol in the Quick Search box to get started. [tutorial 1]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Template Queries. FlyMine has a powerful query interface that can run arbitrary queries on the integrated database. A library of pre-defined ('template') queries that simply require filling in a form is available. Find lists of templates on each aspect page or using the Template Search box below. [tutorial 2].
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Design your own query. Advanced users can use a flexible query interface to construct their own queries. You can save queries you have created for future use and create your own templates. See the user manual and tutorials for more information.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
      FlyMine is updated regularly, adding new data, tools and user interface features. For an idea of what is coming up see the [roadmap]. If there is any data you would like to see added to FlyMine please contact us.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>More about FlyMine</title>

    <para>FlyMine is an integrated web-based database of genomic,
    expression and proteomics data for Drosophila, Anopheles and other
    insects, built to complement existing resources such as
    FlyBase. With the completion of increasing numbers of genome
    sequences has come an explosion in the development of both
    computational and experimental high-throughput techniques for
    deciphering the functions of molecules and their
    interactions. These techniques include theoretical methods for
    deducing function such as analysis of protein homologies,
    structural domain predictions, phylogenetic profiling and protein
    domain fusions and empirical methods such as microarray gene
    expression studies, two-hybrid protein-protein interaction
    experiments, protein co-immunoprecipitation and large-scale RNAi
    screens.  The result is a huge amount of data, and the challenge
    is to extract meaningful knowledge and patterns of biological
    significance that can lead to new experimentally testable
    hypotheses.  Many of these high-throughput data-sets, however, are
    noisy and the data quality can vary significantly.  While for
    certain objectives each of these techniques is useful in its own
    right, stronger inferences can be made if one is able to combine
    data from different sources. Currently biological data are stored
    in a wide variety of formats in numerous different places, making
    such complex queries across these data sources hard.  One of the
    current challenges for bioinformatics is therefore to develop
    resources for the integration and combined analysis of such
    data.</para>

    <para>The FlyMine database is built using <ulink
    url="http://www.intermine.org">InterMine</ulink>, which was
    developed as an integral part of the FlyMine project. InterMine is
    an open-source data warehouse system for integrating data from
    many sources into one object-based database. The FlyMine data
    model is generated by merging existing and emerging ontologies and
    standards (e.g. MAGE, SO, PSI), thus enabling data to be loaded
    from a variety of sources and providing the flexibility to easily
    incorporate new data sources as they appear. A powerful and
    flexible query interface to these data enables users to perform
    arbitrary and complex queries across the data either via a web
    interface or a programming interface. The web interface enables
    users to build queries, by combining classes of objects and
    applying constraints to their attributes. Queries and sets of
    results can be saved for use in further queries or for feeding to
    analysis programs. The result display includes links to external
    databases, class and attribute browsing capability as well as the
    ability to select data for download in a variety of formats. In
    addition, a number of predefined template queries and a browse
    utility provide easier and more direct access to the data. Genome
    sequence features can be viewed with the integrated GBrowse genome
    viewer and protein structures can be viewed and analysed with the
    JMol Java applet. Additional display and analysis tools will be
    available soon. Help is available through query examples,
    tutorials, on-line help pages and an analysis support
    help-desk.</para>

    <para>The first release of FlyMine includes genome annotation data
    for Drosophila melanogaster and Anopheles gambiae, yeast 2-hybrid
    data for D.  melanogaster and C. elegans, and orthologue/
    paralogue data relating the genes of these organisms. The
    inclusion of Caenorhabditis elegans orthologues also gives access
    to C. elegans RNAi phenotypes. 3-D strcutural domain predictions
    for several D. melanogaster proteins are also
    included. Development of the database is currently rapid. We aim
    to add new functional genomics data sources and increase coverage
    to further insects as data become available, as well as
    maintaining continued development of the web interface and
    analysis tools. We hope that FlyMine will become a valuable data
    mining tool for the insect genomics community.</para>
  </section>
</article>
