<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?> 
<article>
  <section>
    <title>What can I do with FlyMine?</title>
    <para>
      FlyMine is an integrated database of genomic, expression and
      protein data for <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>Anopheles</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Integrating data makes it
      possible to run sophisticated data mining queries that span
      domains of biological knowledge.
    </para>
    
    <verbatim><h3>Quick Search</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      Enter any identifier or symbol in the search box on the FlyMine
      home page to access summary pages and integrated tools. For
      example, for the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> gene zen, type
      FBgn0004053, CG1046, zen or any of its synonyms. For an
      <emphasis>Anopheles</emphasis> gene, use the
      <ulink url="http://www.ensembl.org/Anopheles_gambiae/index.html">Ensembl</ulink> 
      identifiers (eg. ENSANGG00000001499), and for a
      <emphasis>C.elegans gene</emphasis>, use the 
      <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/">WormBase</ulink>
      indentifier (eg.T05A10.1d). Where possible, the indentifier for
      a protein is the UniProt identifier (eg. 18C_DROME). 
      <ulink url="doc/tutorials/quickSearch.xml">Tutorial 1</ulink>
    </para>
        
    <verbatim><h3>Browse Aspects</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      FlyMine presents data as 'aspects', with each aspect providing a
      'view' of a particular type of data (for example Gene Expression
      or Protein Interactions). Use the aspect icons on the FlyMine
      home page to run a predefined template query or to build your
      own query (see below). Certain template queries, as well as the
      QueryBuilder itself, allow you to perform searches that span
      more than one aspect.
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>Run Template Queries</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      A number of specific queries have been predefined. These template queries range from 
      fairly simple queries involving just that data type to more complex queries that 
      involve data sets from other aspects as well. More template queries will be added 
      as FlyMine develops and we welcome suggestions. Find lists of predefined template 
      queries on each aspect page or use the Template Search box on the FlyMine home page 
      or in the top menu on every page. 
      <ulink url="doc/tutorials/templates.xml">Tutorial 2</ulink>
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>FlyMine QueryBuilder</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      Advanced users can use a flexible query interface to construct
      their own data mining queries across the multiple integrated
      data sources, to modify existing template queries or to create
      your own template queries. Access the FlyMine QueryBuilder via
      the FlyMine home page or choose a query starting point on an
      aspect page.
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>Operate on Lists</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      All queries in FlyMine can be performed on lists (or
      '<emphasis>bags</emphasis>') that you create yourself. Bags can
      be created by typing or pasting in a list of identifiers, or
      uploading a file containing the list. Data from previous queries
      can also be saved into a bag using the boxes displayed
      underneath the query results. Saved bags of data can be used to
      constrain new queries, perform logical operations and can be
      exported.
    </para>

    <verbatim><h3>Save Queries</h3></verbatim>
    <para>
      You can save your bags, queries and templates by 
      <ulink url="/login.do">creating an account</ulink> using the 'Log in' box
      in the top menu on every page.
    </para>

    <verbatim><br/></verbatim>
    <verbatim><br/></verbatim>

    <para>
      See the <ulink url="doc/tutorials/index.xml">short tutorials</ulink> and 
      <ulink url="doc/manual/index.xml">user manual</ulink> for more information.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
</article>

