<aspects>
  <aspect name="Genomics">
    <subtitle>Genome annotation</subtitle>
    <icon-image>model/images/genomics.gif</icon-image>
    <large-image>model/images/genomics.gif</large-image>
    <intro-text>
      The gene structures and other genome annotations in RatMine are 
			provided by a variety of curated source databases including RGD, 
			NCBI and Ensembl.
    </intro-text>
    <tile-name>model/genomics.jsp</tile-name>
    <aspect-source name="RGD" url="http://rgd.mcw.edu"/>
	<aspect-source name="Ensembl" url="http://www.ensembl.org/Rattus_norvegicus/Info/Index"/>
	<aspect-source name="Wikipedia" url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene" />
  </aspect>

  <aspect name="Quantitative Trait Loci">
	<subtitle></subtitle>
	<icon-image>model/images/QTL_image_197x153.gif</icon-image>
	<large-image>model/images/QTL_image_197x153.gif</large-image>
	<intro-text>
		A Quantitative Trait Locus (QTL) is a genomic region which has been statistically 
		determined by intensive genetic crossing in rats or population studies in human to 
		contain one or more elements linked to a measurable phenotypic trait.  QTL data in 
		RatMine has been manually curated by the Rat Genome Database.
	</intro-text>
	<tile-name>model/QTL.jsp</tile-name>
	<aspect-source name="QTL" url="http://rgd.mcw.edu/rgdweb/search/qtls.html?100"/>
	<aspect-source name="Wikipedia" url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene" />
  </aspect>

  <aspect name="Single Nucleotide Polymorphism">
	<subtitle></subtitle>
	<icon-image>model/images/snp_image.jpg</icon-image>
	<large-image>model/images/snp_image.jpg</large-image>
	<intro-text>
  		A single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP, pronounced snip) is a DNA sequence variation occurring when a single nucleotide (A, T, C, or G) in the genome (or other shared sequence) differs between members of a species (or between paired chromosomes in an individual).
	</intro-text>
	<tile-name>model/SNP.jsp</tile-name>
	<aspect-source name="Ensembl" url="http://www.ensembl.org/Rattus_norvegicus/Info/Index"/>
	<aspect-source name="Wikipedia" url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-nucleotide_polymorphism" />
  </aspect>

  <aspect name="Proteins">
    <subtitle>Protein and proteomics&lt;br/&gt;data</subtitle>
    <icon-image>model/images/proteins.png</icon-image>
    <large-image>model/images/proteins.png</large-image>
    <intro-text>
      RatMine includes protein data such as sequences, family associations, 
			domain structures and gene associations downloaded from the UniProt Knowledgebase.   
    </intro-text>
    <tile-name>model/proteins.jsp</tile-name>
    <aspect-source name="UniProt" url="http://www.uniprot.org"/>
	<aspect-source name="Wikipedia" url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein" />
  </aspect>

  <aspect name="Gene Ontology">
    <subtitle></subtitle>
    <icon-image>model/images/geneOntology.png</icon-image>
    <large-image>model/images/geneOntology.png</large-image>
    <intro-text>
      The Gene Ontology (GO) is a combination of three controlled, 
	  hierarchical vocabularies designed to describe the molecular functions, 
	  biological processes and cellular components of gene products 
	  in a species-independent manner.  GO annotations for rat genes in 
	  RatMine have been supplied by the Rat Genome Database.
    </intro-text>
    <tile-name>model/GO.jsp</tile-name>
    <aspect-source name="Gene Ontology Consortium" url="http://www.geneontology.org/"/>
  </aspect>

  <aspect name="Disease">
    <subtitle>Disease Ontology</subtitle>
    <icon-image>model/images/do.png</icon-image>
    <large-image>model/images/do.png</large-image>
    <intro-text>
			The Rat Genome Database Disease Ontology (DO) is a controlled, 
			hierarchical vocabulary based on the National Library of Medicine's 
			Medical Subject Headings (MeSH).  RGD manually assigns DO terms to rat 
			genes, QTLs and strains, human genes and QTLs and mouse genes based on data 
			from primary research articles.   DO annotations for Rattus norvegicus, 
			supplied by RGD, have been loaded into RatMine and linked to the corresponding 
			genes such that the information available for each gene includes a list of its DO annotations.
    </intro-text>
    <tile-name>model/DO.jsp</tile-name>
  </aspect>  

  <aspect name="Pathway">
    <subtitle></subtitle>
    <icon-image>model/images/pw.png</icon-image>
    <large-image>model/images/pw.png</large-image>
    <intro-text>
			The Pathway Ontology (PW) is a controlled, hierarchical vocabulary designed to 
			describe a variety of biological networks and the relationships between them, 
			including classic metabolic pathways, regulatory pathways, signaling pathways 
			and disease pathways.  PW assignments in RatMine have been manually curated by 
			the Rat Genome Database.
    </intro-text>
    <tile-name>model/PW.jsp</tile-name>
    <aspect-source name="Pathway Ontology" url="http://rgd.mcw.edu/wg/pathway?100"/>
  </aspect> 
  
  <aspect name="Mammalian Phenotype">
    <subtitle></subtitle>
    <icon-image>model/images/mp.png</icon-image>
    <large-image>model/images/mp.png</large-image>
    <intro-text>
			The Mammalian Phenotype (MP) Ontology is a controlled, hierarchical vocabulary developed 
			by Mouse Genome Informatics (MGI) to describe alterations in rat, mouse and human physiology 
			and phenotypes.  Phenotype data for rat genes, QTL and strains  in RatMine has been manually 
			curated by the Rat Genome Database.
    </intro-text>
    <tile-name>model/MP.jsp</tile-name>
    <aspect-source name="Mammalian Phenotype Annotation" url="http://www.informatics.jax.org/searches/MP_form.shtml"/>
  </aspect>
  
</aspects>
