<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->

<article>

<artheader>
<date>2002-6-5</date>
<title>Functional requirements</title>
<authorgroup>
<author>
<firstname>Gos</firstname>
<surname>Micklem</surname>
</author>
<author>
<firstname>Andrew</firstname>
<surname>Varley</surname>
</author>
</authorgroup>
</artheader>

<sect1>
<title>Main aims of the project</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>To create a database for the management of Drosophila and
Anopheles data generated by existing high-throughput post-genomics
techniques: expression studies, proteomics and 3D protein structure
prediction.</listitem>

<listitem>To integrate the above database with the curated database of
Drosophila genetics (FlyBase), the annotated view of the Drosohila
genome (GadFly) and corresponding Anopheles data (AnoBase)</listitem>

<listitem>To enable the database to be queried via the Internet in
order to facilitate the widest possible use by the broader
community.</listitem>

<listitem>To support bulk access to the data for those studying the
entire dataset and for tose generating new analysis
algorithms</listitem>

<listitem>To provide information that will allow other resources to
link to the contents of the database.</listitem>

<listitem>To make the database schema and associated programs freely
available to the community using an open source CVS
repository. Likewise to work collaboratively to generate and promote
the use of public data exchange standards.</listitem>

<listitem>To provide analysis support to facilitate use of the
database and data by the community</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Detailed requirements</title>

<sect2><title>General</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Separate production from development environment</listitem>

<listitem>Release a newly built version of the database every
month</listitem>

<listitem>System to be coded in an organism-independent fashion.</listitem>

<listitem>Expand to cover more of the medically or agriculturally
important pests</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Data sources</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Deal with data from the following microarray sources directly, if not in ArrayExpress:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Affymetrix</listitem>
<listitem>Yale</listitem>
<listitem>Berkeley</listitem>
<listitem>Anopheles</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem>Provide capability to store data from microarrays containing
spotted proteins</listitem>

<listitem>Provide capability to store data from interaction screens
which seek to document global protein-protein interactions</listitem>

<listitem>Store RNAi data</listitem>

<listitem>Import protein data from PDB</listitem>

<listitem>Keep the database up to date with respect to the maturing
gene annotation in Gadfly/Ensembl</listitem>

<listitem>Keep the database up to date with respect to protein
structure predictions as modelling techniques improve over
time. Retain old predictions so that users will not lose the structures
they have been working on.</listitem>

<listitem>Provide several methods of protein structure prediction.</listitem>

<listitem>Store 3D models of protein structure and sequence alignments
that underpin them.</listitem>

<listitem>Store predictions of the full protein structure, for as many
proteins as possible. Failing that, store predictions for parts of
proteins.</listitem>

<listitem>Identify orthologous genes between all the genomes stored
(using blast, or other method, and maybe with some manual
curation).</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>External liaisons</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Enable other databases (FlyBase, GadFly, AnoBase) to link to
us.</listitem>

<listitem>Work to establish public standards for proteomics
data</listitem>

<listitem>Liaise directly with protemics labs until a proteomics
repository is established (similar to ArrayExpress).</listitem>

<listitem>Provide annotation to SwissProt</listitem>

<listitem>Have the GMOD site link to FlyMine</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Data analysis/viewing</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Facilitate easy incorporation of external analysis/viewing tools. Those already existing include:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Expression Profiler from EBI</listitem>
<listitem>Analysis of time-series data (White lab, Yale)</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem>View mutations, genetic variations, alternative splicing and
protein modifications in the context of known and predicted
structures.</listitem>

<listitem>Compare expression levels (with confidence values) in
different experiments by means of replicate spots and
experiments.</listitem>

<listitem>Given 2 annotions of the genome (eg. gadfly and ensembl) and
a score metric, generate a set of annotation features that marks
maximally different spans.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>


</sect2>

<sect2><title>Data access</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Allow rapid, complex, multi-source queries.</listitem>

<listitem>Allow comparison of proteome and transcriptome data derived
from the same sample</listitem>

<listitem>Provide DAS functionality to indicate, for example, the
location of probes on the genome or for which parts of a gene
structure it has been possible to generate comparitive models of
protein structre and how good these predictions are.</listitem>

<listitem>Declare policy of access to data (ie. what volume should we
only supply on tape?)</listitem>

<listitem>Provide an API for querying FlyMine from a remote program to
facilitate use by remote bioinformatics groups.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>User support</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Set up a Users Advisory Board to ensure we are serving the
FlyMine users effectively.</listitem>

<listitem>Maintain logs of activity and feedback received. Solicit
feedback from the regular international fly community conferences and
workshops, and provide a web feedback form for 24 hour user
feedback.</listitem>

<listitem>Run training workshops for the broader community</listitem>

<listitem>Provide support through email, phone and in person</listitem>

<listitem>Provide effective on-line user documentation</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1><title>Future requirements</title>

<para>


It is difficult to present the planned functionality of the data
integration we propose to carry out in words but we attempt to
illustrate the end effect here by means of a few usage scenarios/ few
questions that one should be able to answer by means of the web
interface in browsing mode.  It is also intended to provide a
programming interface that will facilitate the use of the data by
local and remote programs and this will most likely be based on XML,
with the possible use of CORBA at a later date.  For the more routine
methods of gene expression data analysis we intend to use Expression
Profiler by Jaak Vilo of the EBI, which provides a web analysis
interface to gene expression data (** Confirm Jaak's plans - within
DESPRAD ?).


FlyBase --> Post Genomic database links: 
To make an expression link meaningful from a gene it should in some
sense be gene-specific.  As ~all genes will in time be on all arrays,
just linking to the expression database isn't much help.  Things that
could be done or would be useful: Can realistically hope to
automatically generate a ranked list of experimental conditions that
are most likely to be of interest based on those conditions that lead
to the greatest expression differences.

The following curated summaries are probably best left to FlyBase and
in fact something similar already exists so *link to it*.
1) - Link to written summary: 
   "expressed early"
   "expressed in nervous system"
   "expressed all the time"
   "summary of developmental timecourse dataset"

Links from this to appropriate chip experiments or in situ data.

2) - Automatically list expression experiments that have significant/ large
expression differences, allow to access these and find coexpressed
genes and then link back to FlyBase from these.  

3) - Automatically list exps where expression is signif _different_
from WT = "mutants that affect this gene"


> GadFly

  Depict the probes used for making gene expression microarrays in the
  genome browser: clicking on a probe transfers to further data on the
  probe as well as to expression information derived using it.
  Likewise depict the extent of domains /genes for which 3-D
  structural predictions have been made together with an indication of
  the likely reliability of the prediction.  Clicking moves to a
  structure viewer, summary of prediction information and links to
  information in related databases e.g. SCOP.  It would also be useful
  to represent proteins which have been assayed by 2-D PAGE and/ or
  Mass-spectrometry and this indicates that they are resolvable on a
  gel and either a purification protocol exists or they are
  sufficiently abundant to assay directly.  Such information
  facilitates the design of subsequent protein chemistry experiments.

> Gene expression and protein expression data

  MIAME (Minimal Information About a Microarray Experiment) compliant
  experimental annotation is essential to allow such queries to be
  formulated.  We have a joint grant with the EBI to ensure that data
  we produce will conform to the MIAME specification that has been
  devised by the international Microarray Gene Expression Database
  (MGED) group.  The MGED group has also generated a specification for
  microarray markup language (MAML) which specifies how XML can be
  used to transfer microarray data.  By collaborating with the EBI,
  making sure our data is MIAME compliant and being able to read and
  write MAML we should be able to make sure our data is easily usable
  worldwide, and that we are able to receive data from the U.S. groups
  (Spellman (Berkeley) and White (Yale *?*)) which are also producing
  Drosophila gene expression microarray data and are active
  participants in MGED. (*Confirm Kevin's views...*).  In any case we
  intend to keep in contact with these groups to share experience with
  microarray technology and the supporting informatics.

  We propose to develop and apply an experiment annotation scheme
  based on MIAME to the proteomics data which will allow similar
  queries to those on gene expression data.
  - Click through from proteomics experiment report to underlying gene
  annotation in FlyBase.


>Data modelling for queries:

The above data will be modelled as a set of different objects each
with their own distinct set of attributes.  We propose to provide the
ability to collect sets of objects by querying on their attributes and
then to operate on these sets: e.g.

- for a specified experiment, find all the genes that did not have
   significant gene expression changes = set_1

- find the material used for the experiment = set_2.

- find all protein gel experiments using the material in set_2 and
  list the genes with expression differences = set_3.

- Find the common genes in set_1 and set_3 = those genes with
   unchanging steady state mRNA levels but which have alterations in
   protein expression levels.

The sets above can either be lists of the object identifiers, or the
identifiers + specified attributes.  We intend to be able to serve
such sets using XML which will provide a crude method of integration
with remote databases..... *** We need FlyBase to be able to do this in
the first instance...***

This is getting dangerously close to re-creating SRS or acedb in a
relational form.... maybe not good to get into such detail.  On the
other hand we want this functionality so will have to think carefully
about how this can best be done in a very generic fashion.

** Does FlyBase have sufficient set operations ?  Would it in fact
   make most sense to have tags as for GadFly above actually in
   FlyBase so querying is done there followed by link-out ?
   - gene - contains microarray probe - links to probe information and
   experiments which used the probe.
   - gene - marked as having high/ low reliability 3-D predictions(s)
   which link to viewer / information page with further links.
   - gene - marked as having been assayed in proteomics experiment:
   Therefore either abundant and resolvable and/ or has been
   purified.  Links to experiment in either case.  Useful for
   designing future protein chemistry experiments.

</para>
</sect1>
</article>




