<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article>

<artheader>
<date>2002-5-31</date>
<title>Usage Scenarios</title>
<authorgroup>
<author>
<firstname>Gos</firstname>
<surname>Micklem</surname>
</author>
<author>
<firstname>Andrew</firstname>
<surname>Varley</surname>
</author>
</authorgroup>
</artheader>

<sect1>

<para>The system will have five basic data sources: Gadfly, Flybase, 3D
structures, microarrays (gene expression, TF sites), proteomics. Usage
scenarios should cover all combinations.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>Select the proteins in a Gene Ontology functional class (or
some other imported set, or set which is the outcome of an earlier
query), and show the associated gene expression data for them, for
selected experiments.</listitem>

<listitem>List all genes together with their position in the Gene
Ontology for which there is evidence from protein studies of
post-translational modification.</listitem>

<listitem>Find all genes which are not placed in the Gene Ontology for
which there are at least the specified fold expression differences
under a specified minimum number of conditions: list the genes and
conditions.</listitem>

<listitem>Find genes without good structural predictions - extract as
a set of sequences for further study.  Identify those which have been
assayed by 2-D gel and/ or Mass spectrometry, as potential candidates
for structural studies.</listitem>

<listitem>Find genes with significant expression changes under defined
conditions that also occur within a specified map range.</listitem>


<listitem>Find those 3-D structure predictions that are marked as
reliable and which are TIM barrels.  List the gene ontology functions
for these genes.  Find which of these have mutant alleles defined at
the sequence level and paint these onto the structure.</listitem>

<listitem>Find the genes with significant mRNA or protein expression
differences under specified conditions that also occur within a
specified map range. Is anything known about post-translational
modifications of this protein under specified conditions?</listitem>

<listitem>Return set of proteins for which any post-translational
modification is known in a specified set of conditions. Show the ones
that change within the conditions.</listitem>

<listitem>Paint location of mutation/alleles onto the predicted
structure for a gene.</listitem>

<listitem>Start with list of genes. Apply GO contraints (eg. signal
transduction). Return list of Swissprot IDs. Filter by organism
type. Use Drosophila ones to pull out their chromosomal locations from
ensembl. Match Dros. ones with Anoph. gene annotation, and find
chromosomal location. Combine Dros. and Anoph. locations by means of a
mapping based on the underlying genes.</listitem>

<listitem>Microarray experiment analysis to list of genes and list of
corresponding probes. Go to genes on the genome. Extract defined
length of 5' upstream region and generate sequence set. Save in FASTA
format to a file. Apply adhoc program for a common subsequence
search. Build model from list of hits with another adhoc program. Use
another program to do a whole genome search. Identify nearby genes and
list them as possible targets. View the microarry data for these
genes, allowing visual inspection. The scenario means we need to make
registration of external programs easy. Their use should be equivalent
to running a query so their use should be able to be chained
together. NB in an ideal world we might publish interfaces for working
with different objects and allow remote people to register their own
programs to use them. It is not obvious how to get the data back,
except by having the convential API accept lists of object
identifiers, as planned. Is this user authentication and permissions
issue what the GRID is all about??</listitem>

<listitem>Extract subsets of the expression data by querying on
experiment type, experimental conditions, date, laboratory, genetic
background, developmental stage etc e.g.
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Find all the gene expression and protein timecourse
experiments done this year using material from wnt-
flies.</listitem>

<listitem>Find all experiments in which twist varies by more than 4
fold.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem>For a specified spotted PCR product, view the annotated
genome containing the probe.</listitem>

<listitem>For the genes with interesting expression patterns determined with
 Expression Profiler:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>click through to FlyBase to browse further information.</listitem>
<listitem>find subset that have been assayed at protein level and list
with both specified protein and specified gene attributes.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem>For protein just characterised by Mass spec
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>what is known about the structure ?</listitem>
<listitem>is it expressed at a particular developmental stage ?</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>


<listitem>XREFdb-like functionality.</listitem>

<listitem>Allow regexp matching to annotation, eg: Find repeat of less
than 1kb, then gene, then repeat of more than 1kb, in the whole
genome.</listitem>

</itemizedlist>


</sect1>
</article>
