<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<article>

    <artheader>
        <title>001 - Emails</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>François</firstname>
                <surname>Guillier</surname>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
        <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
    </artheader>

    <sect1>
        <title>Quick presentation</title>

        <para>The FlyMine Project has its own domain <emphasis>@flymine.org</emphasis> but users may also have aliases like <emphasis>@gen.cam.ac.uk</emphasis>. All emails are kept on a FlyMine private server.</para>

        <sect2>
            <title>Rules to compose the address</title>

            <para>Each user can use either:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>their login name (ex: bb123@flymine.org)</listitem>
                <listitem>the firstname.lastname form (ex: bilbo.baggins@flymine.org)</listitem>
                <listitem>the initial.lastname form (ex: b.baggins@flymine.org)</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Client settings</title>

            <para>Users are free to choose the MUA (i.e. email client) they want as long as it doesn't run directly on the server and is compatible with either IMAPS or POP3S. IMAPS is recommended since emails stay on the server but can easily deal with synchronisation and off-line reading.</para>

            <para>The settings are the following:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Username: the login name on the FlyMine network</listitem>
                <listitem>Secure POP (incoming mail):
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>server: mail.flymine.org</listitem>
                        <listitem>port (internal network only for now): 995 [the change should be automatic when you select &quot;user SSL encryption&quot;]</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>Secure IMAP (incoming mail):
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>server: mail.flymine.org</listitem>
                        <listitem>port: 993 [the change should be automatic when you select &quot;user SSL encryption&quot;]</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>Outgoing mail/SMTP (on the internal network only):
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>server: mail.flymine.org</listitem>
                        <listitem>port 25</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Mailing lists</title>

            <para>Some addresses are just aliases with one or several recipients. The following addresses are currently open:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>all@flymine.org</listitem>
                <listitem>cvs-admin@flymine.org</listitem>
                <listitem>info@flymine.org</listitem>
                <listitem>postgres@flymine.org</listitem>
                <listitem>postmaster@flymine.org</listitem>
                <listitem>webmaster@flymine.org</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>In addition, there is a true mailing list manager (<filename>mailman</filename>) with subscription system, web access, archives, etc... These lists exist:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>flymine-announce</listitem>
                <listitem>flymine-dev</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>More information about the system</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Mail transport</title>

            <para>As FlyMine is using the Cambridge University networks, both inbound and outbound traffic is passing through the <filename>ppsw.cam.ac.uk</filename> cluster of servers. One of the advantages is the mail is kept in case of unavailability of the FlyMine server but it also means there is no control at all on the queue.</para>
            <para>For security reasons, normal POP and IMAP which allow clear text password are not available even on the internal network.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Imap Server</title>

            <para>The previous "University of Washington IMAP" server has been replaced by Cyrus Imap. Among the new features, the most useful might be possibility of creating nested folders. Messages are kept on specific repository and are not visible at the filesystem level for a normal user (they are owned by "cyrus"). The (user) email filtering is done by "sieve" not by exim.</para>
        </sect2>

         <sect2>
            <title>Server</title>

            <para>The mail server (<filename>flymine.flymine.org</filename>) resides in the DMZ and is actually shared with some other services like DNS, CVS, Web, etc... The integrity of data is provided by disk mirroring. There is currently no backup policy.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

</article>
