<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <date>2002-11-15</date>

    <title>Graphical Query Examples</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Mark</firstname>

        <surname>Woodbridge</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Richard</firstname>

        <surname>Smith</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>This document presents examples of how a number of FlyMine use cases
  could be represented in a graphical query builder. Use Cases taken from
  document by Gos Micklem, Andrew Varley</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Select the proteins in a Gene Ontology functional class, and show
      the associated gene expression data for them, for selected
      experiments.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_1.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>List all genes together with their position in the Gene Ontology
      for which there is evidence from protein studies of post-translational
      modification.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_2.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Find all genes which are not placed in the Gene Ontology for which
      there are at least the specified number of fold expression differences
      under a specified minimum number of conditions: list the genes and
      conditions.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_3.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Find genes without good structural predictions - extract as a set
      of sequences for further study. Identify those which have been assayed
      by 2-D gel and/ or Mass spectrometry, as potential candidates for
      structural studies.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_4.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Find genes with significant expression changes under defined
      conditions that also occur within a specified map range.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_5.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Find those 3-D structure predictions that are marked as reliable
      and which are TIM barrels. List the gene ontology functions for these
      genes. Find which of these have mutant alleles defined at the sequence
      level and paint these onto the structure.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_6.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Find the genes with significant mRNA or protein expression
      differences under specified conditions that also occur within a
      specified map range. Is anything known about post-translational
      modifications of this protein under specified conditions?</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_7.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Return set of proteins for which any post-translational
      modification is known in a specified set of conditions. Show the ones
      that change within the conditions.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_8.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Paint location of mutation/alleles onto the predicted structure
      for a gene.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_9.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Start with list of genes. Apply GO constraints (eg. signal
      transduction). Return list of Swissprot IDs. Filter by organism type.
      Use Drosophila ones to pull out their chromosomal locations from
      ensembl. Match Dros. ones with Anoph. gene annotation, and find
      chromosomal location. Combine Dros. and Anoph. locations by means of a
      mapping based on the underlying genes.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_10.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>For a specified spotted PCR product, view the annotated genome
      containing the probe.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="use_case_11.png" />
        </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</article>
