<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE set PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">


<set>
  <title>FlyMine Cookbook</title>

<book id="flymineCookbook">
  <title>
    FlyMine Cookbook.
  </title>

  <bookinfo>
    <productname>
      <emphasis>FlyMine</emphasis> - An integrated database for Drosophila and
      Anopheles genomics 
    </productname>
  </bookinfo>

<chapter id="HowTo">

   <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>The coookbook provides a series of example queries and
      show you how they can be built in the query builder.  A basic
      knowledge of the query builder is assumed (e.g. how to add
      navigate the model browser, add a constraint and select fields
      for your results output).  If you are not familar with these
      then please see the tutorials first.</para>

</chapter>

  <chapter id="GO_annotation">    
   <title>GO annotation queries</title>

   <sect1 id="GO_annotation1">
           <title>How do I find which GO terms my gene has been annotated with?</title>
	
	<para>A template query is available for this query: </para>

	<para>Gene --> GO terms, which can be accessed via the 'Gene Ontology' aspect.</para>

	<para>To build this query in the query builder:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the class from which you will start
          building your query: from the query builder tab on the home
          page, select 'Gene'.  </para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="GO_query2.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>

	  </listitem>



        <listitem>
          <para>Constrain the Gene class to the Gene of interest by
          adding a constraint to either the Gene identifier, symbol or
          organismdbid.
          </para>

       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="GO_query1.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>


        </listitem>
	

       <listitem>
          <para>Select the 'Summary' button next to 'Gene' to add the
          key gene fields to your output.  Alternatively use the
          'Show' buttons to select individual fields that you would
          like to see in your results.
          </para>


       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="GO_query3.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>


        </listitem>
	

       <listitem>
          <para> Looking down the list of classes in the model browser
          you will notice one called 'allGoAnnotation' and one called
          'goAnnotation'.  The goAnnotation class holds only the
          deepest level GO term annotation (ie the primary annotation
          assignment). The allGoAnnotation class holds all the parents
          of the primary annotation assignment as well.  So, depending
          on whether you want to return only the most specific GO
          terms or the most specific GO terms and all of the parents
          of these GO terms, you will choose either the goAnnotation
          class or the allGoAnnotation class respectively. If you
          expand each of these classes (using the '+' to the left of
          the class name), you will see that the fields available are
          the same for both. Click on 'show' next to 'idenitifer' and
          'name' to return the GO annotation identifier and name.
          Alternatively click on 'summary' to return the key fields.
          </para>



       <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="GO_query4.png" />
          </imageobject><textobject><phrase> </phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>


        </listitem>
	

      <listitem>
          <para>Run the query by pressing 'Show Results'.
          </para>

        </listitem>
	
</orderedlist>



      </sect1>


</chapter>




  <chapter id="RegulatoryRegions">    
   <title>Regulatory region queries</title>

  <sect1 id="RR_1">
           <title>How do I find regulatory regions associated with a gene?</title>
	
	<para>A template query is available for this query: </para>

</sect1>

</chapter>




</book>
</set>
