<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article>

<artheader>
<date>2004-8-20</date>
<title>ISMB 2004</title>
<authorgroup>
<author>
<firstname>Richard</firstname>
<surname>Smith</surname>
</author>
<author>
<firstname>Mark</firstname>
<surname>Woodbridge</surname>
</author>
</authorgroup>
</artheader>


<sect1>
<title>Overview</title>
<para>
The feeling I got was that the big interest this year was in ontologies and graph handling.
Submission of papers and attendance to the ontology sessions vastly exceeded the organisers
expectations.  Graphs were addressed in a considerable number of talks/posters - either
with reference to pathways or describing ontologies.  There seems to a need to ask more
sophisticated questions of ontologies (and ulitmately of pathways).  IBM gave a talk about 
new graph querying functionality proposed for DB2 with some interesting examples.  Oracle 
are working on similar technology.  Manchester University's instance Store (see below) is 
the most sophisticated system for I saw for ontology querying.  The graph querying tutorial 
was interesting and hopefully will prove useful.
</para>

<para>
I think last year a major interest seemed to be data integration, this is something
a number of groups have made progress in.  Major efforts seem to be SeqHound,
and EnsMart/BioMart.  There are others.  Many other sites seem to be enriching their 
data by adding related information.  GO terms seem to be fairly uniquitous now.
</para>

<para>
Also there were some interesting papers on sophisticated approaches to data integration.
In particular dealing with multiple answers for the same piece of data, either by
some automated priority system (based on MetaData) or user preferences.  See talks
65 and 66 in the proceedings.
</para>

<para>
From a technical point of view - Object/Relational mapping is now used in many projects,
probably a fairly even split between OJB and Hibernate, some groups have their own
implementations (e.g. I think aMaze).  Also a number of projects are using automatic
code generation.  I think this can only be good for the acceptance of InterMine over,
say, BioMart.  If it is generally accepted that model-driven architecture is a good
idea and that it is easier to interface with objects then groups are more likely to use
a generic tool that performs those functions.
</para>


<title>InterMine Interest</title>
<para>
The InterMine talk at BOSC didn't generate any significant response, perhaps partly
due to being almost at the end of the second day.  I think it would have been better if
similar projects were grouped in themed sessions with a chance for discussion.  I have
suggested this to the organisers.
</para>

<para>
Rasmus Fogh from Biochemistry suggested that if we are incorporating protein structure 
data we might like to look at the model developed as part of 
<ulink url="http://www.ccpn.ac.uk/datamodel/datamodel.html">CCPN</ulink>.  He also 
expressed some interest in perhaps using InterMine though we have discussed this 
before and the achitecture they have developed serves a similar purpose.
</para>
<para>
The response at the poster sessions was much better, around 50-60 handouts were taken and
we talked to quite a lot of people.  There does seem to be an interest in simple,
configurable data integration.  I don't think InterMine is quite in that position yet but
it could be.   Perhaps four of five people seemed to be considering further investigation
of the system.  In particular Sean Walsh of the John Innes Centre (and formerly the Sanger)
is interested in deploying InterMine, we said we could provide assistance which should 
help us identify areas that need to be made easier/better documented.  He has not yet been
in touch.
</para>

<title>FlyMine Interest</title>
<para>
Rachel could perhaps comment better on interest in FlyMine.
</para>


<title>BOSC</title>
<ulink url="http://open-bio.org/bosc2004/schedule.html">Schedule</ulink>, 
<ulink url="http://open-bio.org/bosc2004/accepted_abstracts.html#abstracts">Abstracts</ulink>

<para>
On the whole could have been more interesting.  A number of long talks were simply updates on
popular projects - e.g. ensembl, BioJava, BioRuby/KEGG.  What might have been more interesting
is some discussion of the state of open source development in life sciences and its promotion,
licensing, funding and so on.  Also grouping talks into themed sessions with an opportunity for
more general discussion.  This sounds like it is the way other SIGs work.
</para>


<title>Projects relevant to InterMine/FlyMine</title>
<sect2>

<title>Manchester University - instance Store</title>
<ulink url="http://instancestore.man.ac.uk/">http://instancestore.man.ac.uk</ulink>
<para>
A group at Manchester who have been working with semantic web technology for some time
have developed an <ulink url="http://instancestore.man.ac.uk/">instance Store</ulink>.
This combines an OQL type database (their own implementation) with an OWL-DL reasoner 
to permit graph type queries on ontologies.  They presented an example using this to 
query the Gene Ontology and associated annotation.  
Similar functionality would be required for InterMine to perform more sophisticated queries 
over ontologies.  I spoke with Phillip Lord, it seems we have significant overlap in
functionality and interest.  We hope to speak further at some point in the future, they
can certainly provide us with ideas on querying ontologies.  In turn Phillip expressed
an interest in our mechanism of integrating data via ontologies/OWL.
</para>


<title>BioJava 2</title>
<ulink url="http://bjv2.derkholm.net">http://bjv2.derkholm.net</ulink>
<para>
Matthew Pocock (and soon other BioJava developers) has been working on the next generation
of BioJava.  This looks very interesting.  It will be heavily based around ontologies and 
code generation from RDF.  We spent some time talking to Matthew and it seems he is trying 
to solve some similar problems to us (and some more complicated ones).  It is very early days
at the moment but may be out of Beta soon.  We hope to talk more about integrating with 
BioJava2 and sharing ideas when we look in more detail at ontology querying.
</para>
<para>
BioJava 2 will reportedly support a generic query language, ontology support, and some 
data integration capabilities.
</para>


<title>BioMart</title>
<ulink url="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomart/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomart</ulink>
<para>
BioMart seems to have a number of installations now.  The suite of tools available
is quite impressive.  Generation of a displays/query templates for new datasets is
controlled by XML configuration, possibly with some default behaviour.  MartEditor is
a GUI to manipulate this configuration.  I think MartEditor can also look at source
datasets and make a naive guess at how to integrate them plus automate the addition
of new tables.
</para>
<para>
MartShell allows some slightly more
interesting queries than the web interface.  MartExplorer is a GUI for building queries,
I haven't looked at this.  The project is impressive and probably suits the needs
of many people.  It doesn't, however, offer the same level of flexibility of querying
that InterMine.  There is still a coupling between the schema and possible queries,
therefore one could only run the types of queries thought of at build time.
</para>


<title>Microarray posters</title>
<para>
A number of groups are setting up their own systems for publishing their microarray results instead
of using ArrayExpress.  Their comments were that it is just too complicated to submit their
data to ArrayExpress.  Some projects seem to be able to generate MAGE-ML from their software
and some LIMS/commercial microarray software(?) should be able to output it directly.
</para>

<title>UniProt</title>
<ulink url="http://www.uniprot.org">http://www.uniprot.org</ulink>
<para>
UniProt now make their data <ulink url="http://www.uniprot.org/database/download.shtml">available</ulink>
 in an XML format.  This is <ulink url="http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot.xsd">defined</ulink> 
by XML Schema.
</para>
<para>
Of all the web interfaces demonstrated, <ulink url="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/index.html">IntAct</ulink> 
and <ulink url="http://www.ebi.uniprot.org/index.shtml">UniProt</ulink> seemed fairly clean, and 
implemented some operations that we support (bags, browsing) quite well. intact in particular has 
some nice vizualisation bits for graphs and interaction networks. for us, some really basic text 
search (as a template?) would be a good place to start for absolute beginners. 
</para>


<title>Taverna</title>
<ulink url="http://taverna.sourceforge.net">http://taverna.sourceforge.net</ulink>
<para>
A slick, general purpose system to link "services" together, which may implemented locally (eg. string 
manipulation) or remotely (eg. sequence retrieval), to build a workflow for a particular task. Slick 
and usable (Swing?) interface. provides an interface to other service providers (eg. seqhound) and 
service registries (eg. biomoby).
</para>
<para>
Taverna possibly makes use of the <ulink url="http://www.mygrid.org.uk">mygrid</ulink> controlled 
vocabulary of bioinformatics concepts, which could be useful in describing other web services. 
</para>

<title>EBI webservices</title>
<ulink url="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/webservices/services.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/webservices/services.html</ulink>
<para>
The EBI are exposing some services remotely - it would be worth seeing the APIs they expose, 
and how they handle (or defer) large requests. their approach might be a good one to model for 
exposing our template queries as remote services. This would get us a foothold in biomoby etc. 
The plan here is to expose simple queries that demonstrate the advantages of the extent to which 
we integrate data. 
</para>

<title>Electric Genetics - BioPerl validation</title>
<ulink url="http://www.egenetics.com/opensource.html">http://www.egenetics.com/epensource.html</ulink>
<para>
Perhaps not relevent to us but an interesting <ulink url="http://open-bio.org/bosc2004/accepted_abstracts.html#vanheusen">talk</ulink> about a commercial test suite for BioPerl which they supply at a cost to other companies along with
BioPerl support.
</para>

<title>Blueprint</title>
<ulink url="http://www.blueprint.org">http://www.blueprint.org</ulink>
<para>
The Blueprint project, based in Canada, and <ulink url="http://www.blueprint.org/seqhound/seqhound.html">seqhound</ulink>
in particular, seemed to getting a lot of interest. it's some form of integrated database, 
but i haven't looked at it closely. they are definitely talented self-publicists.
</para>

<title>Life Science Identifiers (LSIDs)/Semantic Web</title>
<ulink url="http://xml.coverpages.org/lsid.html">http://xml.coverpages.org/lsid.html</ulink>
<para>
An interesting idea, and something we should really support.  These, and other relevant Semantic 
Web stuff will be discussed at the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/2004/07/swls-cfp.html">W3C Workshop on Semantic Web</ulink>
for Life Sciences in October.  The Semantic Web meeting was discussing having some cool/useful
technology but no real application that demonstrated it's power.  Perhaps that means its not
actually that useful.  Much of the talk was about online services creating RDF/OWL descriptions
of the data they provide/service they offer with the aim of making the data machine readble/discoverable/integratable.
</para>


<title>DagEdit</title>
<ulink url="http://geneontology.sourceforge.net">http://geneontology.sourceforge.net</ulink>
<para>
Looks quite usable now, and handles the more recent obo ontology format.  It can also draw 
ontology graphs using graphviz.  It can export OWL, but cannot import (because owl is 
too unconstrained).
</para>

<title>BioInformatics Knowledgebase</title>
<ulink url="http://apps.bioneq.qc.ca/twiki/bin/view/Knowledgebase/WebHome">is available here</ulink>
<para>
A useful glossary of terms and a database list.  Especially for non-biologists.  
<ulink url="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/2can/home.html">2can</ulink> is more structured, with 
a more educational bias.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
